<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <respStmt>
            <resp>Text placed in the public domain</resp>
            <name>Moby Lexical Tools, 1992</name>
            <resp>SGML markup</resp>
            <name>Jon Bosak, 1992-1994</name>
            <resp>XML markup</resp>
            <name>Jon Bosak, 1996-1998</name>
            <resp>TEI P5 markup</resp>
            <name>Ian Williams, 2009</name>
         </respStmt>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <docTitle>Love's Labour's Lost</docTitle>

         <div type="cast">
            <castList>
               <head>Dramatis Personae</head>

               <castItem>Ferdinand, King of Navarre.</castItem>

               <castGroup>
                  <castItem>Biron</castItem>
                  <castItem>Longaville</castItem>
                  <castItem>Dumain</castItem>
                  <roleDesc>Lords attending on the King.</roleDesc>
               </castGroup>

               <castGroup>
                  <castItem>Boyet</castItem>
                  <castItem>Mercade</castItem>
                  <roleDesc>Lords attending on the Princess of
                     France.</roleDesc>
               </castGroup>

               <castItem>Don Adriano, a fantastical Spaniard.</castItem>
               <castItem>Sir Nathaniel, a curate.</castItem>
               <castItem>Holofernes, a schoolmaster.</castItem>

               <castItem>Dull, a constable.</castItem>
               <castItem>Costard, a clown.</castItem>
               <castItem>Moth, page to Armado.</castItem>
               <castItem>A Forester.</castItem>
               <castItem>The Princess of France.</castItem>

               <castGroup>
                  <castItem>Rosaline</castItem>
                  <castItem>Maria</castItem>
                  <castItem>Katherine</castItem>

                  <roleDesc>Ladies attending on the Princess.</roleDesc>
               </castGroup>

               <castItem>Jaquenetta, a country wench.</castItem>
               <castItem>Lords, attendants, &amp;c.</castItem>
            </castList>
         </div>

         <set>
            <p>Scene Navarre.</p>
         </set>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act" n="1">
            <div type="scene" n="1">
               <head>The King of Navarre's park.</head>
               <stage>Enter Ferdinand King of Navarre, Biron, Longaville and
                  Dumain</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Let fame, that all hunt after in their lives,</l>
                  <l>Live register'd upon our brazen tombs</l>
                  <l>And then grace us in the disgrace of death;</l>

                  <l>When, spite of cormorant devouring Time,</l>
                  <l>The endeavor of this present breath may buy</l>
                  <l>That honour which shall bate his scythe's keen edge</l>
                  <l>And make us heirs of all eternity.</l>
                  <l>Therefore, brave conquerors,--for so you are,</l>
                  <l>That war against your own affections</l>
                  <l>And the huge army of the world's desires,--</l>
                  <l>Our late edict shall strongly stand in force:</l>
                  <l>Navarre shall be the wonder of the world;</l>

                  <l>Our court shall be a little Academe,</l>
                  <l>Still and contemplative in living art.</l>
                  <l>You three, Biron, Dumain, and Longaville,</l>
                  <l>Have sworn for three years' term to live with me</l>
                  <l>My fellow-scholars, and to keep those statutes</l>
                  <l>That are recorded in this schedule here:</l>
                  <l>Your oaths are pass'd; and now subscribe your names,</l>
                  <l>That his own hand may strike his honour down</l>
                  <l>That violates the smallest branch herein:</l>

                  <l>If you are arm'd to do as sworn to do,</l>
                  <l>Subscribe to your deep oaths, and keep it too.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>I am resolved; 'tis but a three years' fast:</l>
                  <l>The mind shall banquet, though the body pine:</l>
                  <l>Fat paunches have lean pates, and dainty bits</l>
                  <l>Make rich the ribs, but bankrupt quite the wits.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>My loving lord, Dumain is mortified:</l>
                  <l>The grosser manner of these world's delights</l>
                  <l>He throws upon the gross world's baser slaves:</l>
                  <l>To love, to wealth, to pomp, I pine and die;</l>
                  <l>With all these living in philosophy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I can but say their protestation over;</l>
                  <l>So much, dear liege, I have already sworn,</l>
                  <l>That is, to live and study here three years.</l>
                  <l>But there are other strict observances;</l>
                  <l>As, not to see a woman in that term,</l>
                  <l>Which I hope well is not enrolled there;</l>
                  <l>And one day in a week to touch no food</l>

                  <l>And but one meal on every day beside,</l>
                  <l>The which I hope is not enrolled there;</l>
                  <l>And then, to sleep but three hours in the night,</l>
                  <l>And not be seen to wink of all the day--</l>
                  <l>When I was wont to think no harm all night</l>
                  <l>And make a dark night too of half the day--</l>
                  <l>Which I hope well is not enrolled there:</l>
                  <l>O, these are barren tasks, too hard to keep,</l>
                  <l>Not to see ladies, study, fast, not sleep!</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Your oath is pass'd to pass away from these.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Let me say no, my liege, an if you please:</l>
                  <l>I only swore to study with your grace</l>
                  <l>And stay here in your court for three years' space.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>You swore to that, Biron, and to the rest.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>By yea and nay, sir, then I swore in jest.</l>
                  <l>What is the end of study? let me know.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Why, that to know, which else we should not know.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Things hid and barr'd, you mean, from common sense?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>Ay, that is study's godlike recompense.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Come on, then; I will swear to study so,</l>
                  <l>To know the thing I am forbid to know:</l>
                  <l>As thus,--to study where I well may dine,</l>
                  <l>When I to feast expressly am forbid;</l>
                  <l>Or study where to meet some mistress fine,</l>

                  <l>When mistresses from common sense are hid;</l>
                  <l>Or, having sworn too hard a keeping oath,</l>
                  <l>Study to break it and not break my troth.</l>
                  <l>If study's gain be thus and this be so,</l>
                  <l>Study knows that which yet it doth not know:</l>
                  <l>Swear me to this, and I will ne'er say no.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>These be the stops that hinder study quite</l>
                  <l>And train our intellects to vain delight.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Why, all delights are vain; but that most vain,</l>
                  <l>Which with pain purchased doth inherit pain:</l>
                  <l>As, painfully to pore upon a book</l>
                  <l>To seek the light of truth; while truth the while</l>

                  <l>Doth falsely blind the eyesight of his look:</l>
                  <l>Light seeking light doth light of light beguile:</l>
                  <l>So, ere you find where light in darkness lies,</l>
                  <l>Your light grows dark by losing of your eyes.</l>
                  <l>Study me how to please the eye indeed</l>
                  <l>By fixing it upon a fairer eye,</l>
                  <l>Who dazzling so, that eye shall be his heed</l>
                  <l>And give him light that it was blinded by.</l>
                  <l>Study is like the heaven's glorious sun</l>

                  <l>That will not be deep-search'd with saucy looks:</l>
                  <l>Small have continual plodders ever won</l>
                  <l>Save base authority from others' books</l>
                  <l>These earthly godfathers of heaven's lights</l>
                  <l>That give a name to every fixed star</l>
                  <l>Have no more profit of their shining nights</l>
                  <l>Than those that walk and wot not what they are.</l>
                  <l>Too much to know is to know nought but fame;</l>
                  <l>And every godfather can give a name.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>How well he's read, to reason against reading!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Proceeded well, to stop all good proceeding!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>He weeds the corn and still lets grow the weeding.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>The spring is near when green geese are a-breeding.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>How follows that?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Fit in his place and time.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>In reason nothing.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Something then in rhyme.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Biron is like an envious sneaping frost,</l>
                  <l>That bites the first-born infants of the spring.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Well, say I am; why should proud summer boast</l>
                  <l>Before the birds have any cause to sing?</l>
                  <l>Why should I joy in any abortive birth?</l>
                  <l>At Christmas I no more desire a rose</l>
                  <l>Than wish a snow in May's new-fangled mirth;</l>
                  <l>But like of each thing that in season grows.</l>
                  <l>So you, to study now it is too late,</l>
                  <l>Climb o'er the house to unlock the little gate.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Well, sit you out: go home, Biron: adieu.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>No, my good lord; I have sworn to stay with you:</l>
                  <l>And though I have for barbarism spoke more</l>
                  <l>Than for that angel knowledge you can say,</l>

                  <l>Yet confident I'll keep what I have swore</l>
                  <l>And bide the penance of each three years' day.</l>
                  <l>Give me the paper; let me read the same;</l>
                  <l>And to the strict'st decrees I'll write my name.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>How well this yielding rescues thee from shame!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'Item, That no woman shall come within
                     a</l>
                  <l>mile of my court:' Hath this been proclaimed?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Four days ago.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Let's see the penalty.</l>
                  <stage>Reads</stage>
                  <l>'On pain of losing her tongue.' Who devised this
                     penalty?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Marry, that did I.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet lord, and why?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>To fright them hence with that dread penalty.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>A dangerous law against gentility!</l>
                  <stage>Reads</stage>
                  <l>'Item, If any man be seen to talk with a woman</l>
                  <l>within the term of three years, he shall endure such</l>
                  <l>public shame as the rest of the court can possibly
                     devise.'</l>
                  <l>This article, my liege, yourself must break;</l>
                  <l>For well you know here comes in embassy</l>
                  <l>The French king's daughter with yourself to speak--</l>

                  <l>A maid of grace and complete majesty--</l>
                  <l>About surrender up of Aquitaine</l>
                  <l>To her decrepit, sick and bedrid father:</l>
                  <l>Therefore this article is made in vain,</l>
                  <l>Or vainly comes the admired Princess hither.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What say you, lords? Why, this was quite forgot.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>So study evermore is overshot:</l>
                  <l>While it doth study to have what it would</l>
                  <l>It doth forget to do the thing it should,</l>
                  <l>And when it hath the thing it hunteth most,</l>
                  <l>'Tis won as towns with fire, so won, so lost.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>We must of force dispense with this decree;</l>
                  <l>She must lie here on mere necessity.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Necessity will make us all forsworn</l>
                  <l>Three thousand times within this three years' space;</l>
                  <l>For every man with his affects is born,</l>

                  <l>Not by might master'd but by special grace:</l>
                  <l>If I break faith, this word shall speak for me;</l>
                  <l>I am forsworn on 'mere necessity.'</l>
                  <l>So to the laws at large I write my name:</l>
                  <stage>Subscribes</stage>
                  <l>And he that breaks them in the least degree</l>
                  <l>Stands in attainder of eternal shame:</l>
                  <l>Suggestions are to other as to me;</l>
                  <l>But I believe, although I seem so loath,</l>

                  <l>I am the last that will last keep his oath.</l>
                  <l>But is there no quick recreation granted?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, that there is. Our court, you know, is haunted</l>
                  <l>With a refined traveller of Spain;</l>
                  <l>A man in all the world's new fashion planted,</l>
                  <l>That hath a mint of phrases in his brain;</l>

                  <l>One whom the music of his own vain tongue</l>
                  <l>Doth ravish like enchanting harmony;</l>
                  <l>A man of complements, whom right and wrong</l>
                  <l>Have chose as umpire of their mutiny:</l>
                  <l>This child of fancy, that Armado hight,</l>
                  <l>For interim to our studies shall relate</l>
                  <l>In high-born words the worth of many a knight</l>
                  <l>From tawny Spain lost in the world's debate.</l>
                  <l>How you delight, my lords, I know not, I;</l>

                  <l>But, I protest, I love to hear him lie</l>
                  <l>And I will use him for my minstrelsy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Armado is a most illustrious wight,</l>
                  <l>A man of fire-new words, fashion's own knight.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>

                  <l>Costard the swain and he shall be our sport;</l>
                  <l>And so to study, three years is but short.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Dull with a letter, and Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>Which is the duke's own person?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>This, fellow: what wouldst?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>I myself reprehend his own person, for I am his</l>
                  <l>grace's tharborough: but I would see his own person</l>
                  <l>in flesh and blood.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>This is he.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>Signior Arme--Arme--commends you. There's villany</l>
                  <l>abroad: this letter will tell you more.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the contempts thereof are as touching me.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>A letter from the magnificent Armado.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>How low soever the matter, I hope in God for high
                     words.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>A high hope for a low heaven: God grant us patience!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>To hear? or forbear laughing?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>To hear meekly, sir, and to laugh moderately; or to</l>
                  <l>forbear both.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Well, sir, be it as the style shall give us cause to</l>
                  <l>climb in the merriness.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>The matter is to me, sir, as concerning Jaquenetta.</l>
                  <l>The manner of it is, I was taken with the manner.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>In what manner?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>In manner and form following, sir; all those three:</l>
                  <l>I was seen with her in the manor-house, sitting with</l>
                  <l>her upon the form, and taken following her into the</l>
                  <l>park; which, put together, is in manner and form</l>
                  <l>following. Now, sir, for the manner,--it is the</l>
                  <l>manner of a man to speak to a woman: for the form,--</l>
                  <l>in some form.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>For the following, sir?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>As it shall follow in my correction: and God defend</l>
                  <l>the right!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Will you hear this letter with attention?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>As we would hear an oracle.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>Such is the simplicity of man to hearken after the
                     flesh.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'Great deputy, the welkin's vicegerent
                     and</l>
                  <l>sole dominator of Navarre, my soul's earth's god,</l>
                  <l>and body's fostering patron.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Not a word of Costard yet.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'So it is,'--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>It may be so: but if he say it is so, he is, in</l>
                  <l>telling true, but so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Peace!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>Be to me and every man that dares not fight!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>No words!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Of other men's secrets, I beseech you.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'So it is, besieged with
                     sable-coloured</l>
                  <l>melancholy, I did commend the black-oppressing humour</l>
                  <l>to the most wholesome physic of thy health-giving</l>
                  <l>air; and, as I am a gentleman, betook myself to</l>
                  <l>walk. The time when. About the sixth hour; when</l>
                  <l>beasts most graze, birds best peck, and men sit down</l>

                  <l>to that nourishment which is called supper: so much</l>
                  <l>for the time when. Now for the ground which; which,</l>
                  <l>I mean, I walked upon: it is y-cleped thy park. Then</l>
                  <l>for the place where; where, I mean, I did encounter</l>
                  <l>that obscene and preposterous event, that draweth</l>
                  <l>from my snow-white pen the ebon-coloured ink, which</l>
                  <l>here thou viewest, beholdest, surveyest, or seest;</l>
                  <l>but to the place where; it standeth north-north-east</l>
                  <l>and by east from the west corner of thy curious-</l>
                  <l>knotted garden: there did I see that low-spirited</l>
                  <l>swain, that base minnow of thy mirth,'--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Me?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'that unlettered small-knowing
                     soul,'--</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Me?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'that shallow vassal,'--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Still me?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'which, as I remember, hight
                     Costard,'--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>O, me!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'sorted and consorted, contrary to
                     thy</l>
                  <l>established proclaimed edict and continent canon,</l>
                  <l>which with,--O, with--but with this I passion to say</l>

                  <l>wherewith,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>With a wench.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'with a child of our grandmother Eve,
                     a</l>

                  <l>female; or, for thy more sweet understanding, a</l>
                  <l>woman. Him I, as my ever-esteemed duty pricks me on,</l>
                  <l>have sent to thee, to receive the meed of</l>
                  <l>punishment, by thy sweet grace's officer, Anthony</l>
                  <l>Dull; a man of good repute, carriage, bearing, and</l>
                  <l>estimation.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>

                  <l>'Me, an't shall please you; I am Anthony Dull.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Reads</stage> 'For Jaquenetta,--so is the weaker
                     vessel</l>
                  <l>called which I apprehended with the aforesaid</l>
                  <l>swain,--I keep her as a vessel of the law's fury;</l>
                  <l>and shall, at the least of thy sweet notice, bring</l>

                  <l>her to trial. Thine, in all compliments of devoted</l>
                  <l>and heart-burning heat of duty.</l>
                  <l>Don Adriano.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>This is not so well as I looked for, but the best</l>
                  <l>that ever I heard.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, the best for the worst. But, sirrah, what say</l>
                  <l>you to this?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I confess the wench.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Did you hear the proclamation?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I do confess much of the hearing it but little of</l>
                  <l>the marking of it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>It was proclaimed a year's imprisonment, to be taken</l>
                  <l>with a wench.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I was taken with none, sir: I was taken with a damsel.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Well, it was proclaimed 'damsel.'</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>This was no damsel, neither, sir; she was a virgin.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>It is so varied, too; for it was proclaimed 'virgin.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>If it were, I deny her virginity: I was taken with a
                     maid.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>This maid will not serve your turn, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>This maid will serve my turn, sir.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I will pronounce your sentence: you shall fast</l>
                  <l>a week with bran and water.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I had rather pray a month with mutton and porridge.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>And Don Armado shall be your keeper.</l>
                  <l>My Lord Biron, see him deliver'd o'er:</l>
                  <l>And go we, lords, to put in practise that</l>
                  <l>Which each to other hath so strongly sworn.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Ferdinand, Longaville, and Dumain</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I'll lay my head to any good man's hat,</l>
                  <l>These oaths and laws will prove an idle scorn.</l>
                  <l>Sirrah, come on.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I suffer for the truth, sir; for true it is, I was</l>
                  <l>taken with Jaquenetta, and Jaquenetta is a true</l>
                  <l>girl; and therefore welcome the sour cup of</l>
                  <l>prosperity! Affliction may one day smile again; and</l>
                  <l>till then, sit thee down, sorrow!</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>

            <div type="scene" n="2">
               <head>The same.</head>

               <stage>Enter Don Adriano and Moth</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Boy, what sign is it when a man of great spirit</l>
                  <l>grows melancholy?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>A great sign, sir, that he will look sad.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Why, sadness is one and the self-same thing, dear imp.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>No, no; O Lord, sir, no.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>How canst thou part sadness and melancholy, my</l>
                  <l>tender juvenal?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>By a familiar demonstration of the working, my tough
                     senior.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>Why tough senior? why tough senior?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Why tender juvenal? why tender juvenal?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I spoke it, tender juvenal, as a congruent epitheton</l>
                  <l>appertaining to thy young days, which we may</l>

                  <l>nominate tender.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>And I, tough senior, as an appertinent title to your</l>
                  <l>old time, which we may name tough.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Pretty and apt.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>How mean you, sir? I pretty, and my saying apt? or</l>
                  <l>I apt, and my saying pretty?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Thou pretty, because little.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Little pretty, because little. Wherefore apt?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>And therefore apt, because quick.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>Speak you this in my praise, master?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>In thy condign praise.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>I will praise an eel with the same praise.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>What, that an eel is ingenious?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>That an eel is quick.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>I do say thou art quick in answers: thou heatest my
                     blood.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>I am answered, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I love not to be crossed.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside</stage> He speaks the mere contrary; crosses
                     love not him.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I have promised to study three years with the duke.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>You may do it in an hour, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Impossible.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>How many is one thrice told?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I am ill at reckoning; it fitteth the spirit of a
                     tapster.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>You are a gentleman and a gamester, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I confess both: they are both the varnish of a</l>
                  <l>complete man.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Then, I am sure, you know how much the gross sum of</l>
                  <l>deuce-ace amounts to.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>It doth amount to one more than two.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Which the base vulgar do call three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>True.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Why, sir, is this such a piece of study? Now here</l>
                  <l>is three studied, ere ye'll thrice wink: and how</l>
                  <l>easy it is to put 'years' to the word 'three,' and</l>
                  <l>study three years in two words, the dancing horse</l>

                  <l>will tell you.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>A most fine figure!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>To prove you a cipher.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I will hereupon confess I am in love: and as it is</l>
                  <l>base for a soldier to love, so am I in love with a</l>
                  <l>base wench. If drawing my sword against the humour</l>
                  <l>of affection would deliver me from the reprobate</l>
                  <l>thought of it, I would take Desire prisoner, and</l>
                  <l>ransom him to any French courtier for a new-devised</l>
                  <l>courtesy. I think scorn to sigh: methinks I should</l>

                  <l>outswear Cupid. Comfort, me, boy: what great men</l>
                  <l>have been in love?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Hercules, master.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Most sweet Hercules! More authority, dear boy, name</l>

                  <l>more; and, sweet my child, let them be men of good</l>
                  <l>repute and carriage.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Samson, master: he was a man of good carriage, great</l>
                  <l>carriage, for he carried the town-gates on his back</l>
                  <l>like a porter: and he was in love.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>O well-knit Samson! strong-jointed Samson! I do</l>
                  <l>excel thee in my rapier as much as thou didst me in</l>
                  <l>carrying gates. I am in love too. Who was Samson's</l>
                  <l>love, my dear Moth?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>A woman, master.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Of what complexion?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Of all the four, or the three, or the two, or one of the
                     four.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Tell me precisely of what complexion.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Of the sea-water green, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Is that one of the four complexions?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>As I have read, sir; and the best of them too.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Green indeed is the colour of lovers; but to have a</l>
                  <l>love of that colour, methinks Samson had small reason</l>
                  <l>for it. He surely affected her for her wit.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>It was so, sir; for she had a green wit.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>My love is most immaculate white and red.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Most maculate thoughts, master, are masked under</l>
                  <l>such colours.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Define, define, well-educated infant.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>My father's wit and my mother's tongue, assist me!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet invocation of a child; most pretty and</l>
                  <l>pathetical!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <stage>Sings</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If she be made of white and red,</l>
                     <l>Her faults will ne'er be known,</l>
                     <l>For blushing cheeks by faults are bred</l>
                     <l>And fears by pale white shown:</l>
                     <l>Then if she fear, or be to blame,</l>
                     <l>By this you shall not know,</l>
                     <l>For still her cheeks possess the same</l>
                     <l>Which native she doth owe.</l>
                  </lg>

                  <l>A dangerous rhyme, master, against the reason of</l>
                  <l>white and red.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Is there not a ballad, boy, of the King and the Beggar?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>The world was very guilty of such a ballad some</l>
                  <l>three ages since: but I think now 'tis not to be</l>
                  <l>found; or, if it were, it would neither serve for</l>

                  <l>the writing nor the tune.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I will have that subject newly writ o'er, that I may</l>
                  <l>example my digression by some mighty precedent.</l>
                  <l>Boy, I do love that country girl that I took in the</l>
                  <l>park with the rational hind Costard: she deserves well.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside</stage> To be whipped; and yet a better love
                     than</l>
                  <l>my master.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sing, boy; my spirit grows heavy in love.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>And that's great marvel, loving a light wench.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I say, sing.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>Forbear till this company be past.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Dull, Costard, and Jaquenetta</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the duke's pleasure is, that you keep Costard</l>
                  <l>safe: and you must suffer him to take no delight</l>
                  <l>nor no penance; but a' must fast three days a week.</l>

                  <l>For this damsel, I must keep her at the park: she</l>
                  <l>is allowed for the day-woman. Fare you well.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I do betray myself with blushing. Maid!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Man?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I will visit thee at the lodge.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>That's hereby.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I know where it is situate.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Lord, how wise you are!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I will tell thee wonders.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>With that face?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I love thee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>So I heard you say.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>And so, farewell.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Fair weather after you!</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>Come, Jaquenetta, away!</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Dull and Jaquenetta</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Villain, thou shalt fast for thy offences ere thou</l>

                  <l>be pardoned.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Well, sir, I hope, when I do it, I shall do it on a</l>
                  <l>full stomach.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Thou shalt be heavily punished.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I am more bound to you than your fellows, for they</l>
                  <l>are but lightly rewarded.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Take away this villain; shut him up.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Come, you transgressing slave; away!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Let me not be pent up, sir: I will fast, being loose.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>No, sir; that were fast and loose: thou shalt to
                     prison.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Well, if ever I do see the merry days of desolation</l>
                  <l>that I have seen, some shall see.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>What shall some see?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nothing, Master Moth, but what they look upon.</l>
                  <l>It is not for prisoners to be too silent in their</l>
                  <l>words; and therefore I will say nothing: I thank</l>
                  <l>God I have as little patience as another man; and</l>
                  <l>therefore I can be quiet.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Exeunt Moth and Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I do affect the very ground, which is base, where</l>
                  <l>her shoe, which is baser, guided by her foot, which</l>
                  <l>is basest, doth tread. I shall be forsworn, which</l>
                  <l>is a great argument of falsehood, if I love. And</l>
                  <l>how can that be true love which is falsely</l>

                  <l>attempted? Love is a familiar; Love is a devil:</l>
                  <l>there is no evil angel but Love. Yet was Samson so</l>
                  <l>tempted, and he had an excellent strength; yet was</l>
                  <l>Solomon so seduced, and he had a very good wit.</l>
                  <l>Cupid's butt-shaft is too hard for Hercules' club;</l>
                  <l>and therefore too much odds for a Spaniard's rapier.</l>
                  <l>The first and second cause will not serve my turn;</l>
                  <l>the passado he respects not, the duello he regards</l>
                  <l>not: his disgrace is to be called boy; but his</l>

                  <l>glory is to subdue men. Adieu, valour! rust rapier!</l>
                  <l>be still, drum! for your manager is in love; yea,</l>
                  <l>he loveth. Assist me, some extemporal god of rhyme,</l>
                  <l>for I am sure I shall turn sonnet. Devise, wit;</l>
                  <l>write, pen; for I am for whole volumes in folio.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>
            </div>

         </div>

         <div type="act" n="2">
            <div type="scene" n="1">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter the Princess of France, Rosaline, Maria, Katherine,
                  Boyet, Lords, and other Attendants</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Now, madam, summon up your dearest spirits:</l>
                  <l>Consider who the king your father sends,</l>

                  <l>To whom he sends, and what's his embassy:</l>
                  <l>Yourself, held precious in the world's esteem,</l>
                  <l>To parley with the sole inheritor</l>
                  <l>Of all perfections that a man may owe,</l>
                  <l>Matchless Navarre; the plea of no less weight</l>
                  <l>Than Aquitaine, a dowry for a queen.</l>
                  <l>Be now as prodigal of all dear grace</l>
                  <l>As Nature was in making graces dear</l>
                  <l>When she did starve the general world beside</l>

                  <l>And prodigally gave them all to you.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Good Lord Boyet, my beauty, though but mean,</l>
                  <l>Needs not the painted flourish of your praise:</l>
                  <l>Beauty is bought by judgement of the eye,</l>
                  <l>Not utter'd by base sale of chapmen's tongues:</l>
                  <l>I am less proud to hear you tell my worth</l>

                  <l>Than you much willing to be counted wise</l>
                  <l>In spending your wit in the praise of mine.</l>
                  <l>But now to task the tasker: good Boyet,</l>
                  <l>You are not ignorant, all-telling fame</l>
                  <l>Doth noise abroad, Navarre hath made a vow,</l>
                  <l>Till painful study shall outwear three years,</l>
                  <l>No woman may approach his silent court:</l>
                  <l>Therefore to's seemeth it a needful course,</l>
                  <l>Before we enter his forbidden gates,</l>

                  <l>To know his pleasure; and in that behalf,</l>
                  <l>Bold of your worthiness, we single you</l>
                  <l>As our best-moving fair solicitor.</l>
                  <l>Tell him, the daughter of the King of France,</l>
                  <l>On serious business, craving quick dispatch,</l>
                  <l>Importunes personal conference with his grace:</l>
                  <l>Haste, signify so much; while we attend,</l>
                  <l>Like humble-visaged suitors, his high will.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Proud of employment, willingly I go.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>All pride is willing pride, and yours is so.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Boyet</stage>
                  <l>Who are the votaries, my loving lords,</l>

                  <l>That are vow-fellows with this virtuous duke?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
                  <l>Lord Longaville is one.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Know you the man?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>I know him, madam: at a marriage-feast,</l>
                  <l>Between Lord Perigort and the beauteous heir</l>
                  <l>Of Jaques Falconbridge, solemnized</l>
                  <l>In Normandy, saw I this Longaville:</l>
                  <l>A man of sovereign parts he is esteem'd;</l>
                  <l>Well fitted in arts, glorious in arms:</l>
                  <l>Nothing becomes him ill that he would well.</l>

                  <l>The only soil of his fair virtue's gloss,</l>
                  <l>If virtue's gloss will stain with any soil,</l>
                  <l>Is a sharp wit matched with too blunt a will;</l>
                  <l>Whose edge hath power to cut, whose will still wills</l>
                  <l>It should none spare that come within his power.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Some merry mocking lord, belike; is't so?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>They say so most that most his humours know.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Such short-lived wits do wither as they grow.</l>
                  <l>Who are the rest?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>The young Dumain, a well-accomplished youth,</l>
                  <l>Of all that virtue love for virtue loved:</l>
                  <l>Most power to do most harm, least knowing ill;</l>
                  <l>For he hath wit to make an ill shape good,</l>
                  <l>And shape to win grace though he had no wit.</l>
                  <l>I saw him at the Duke Alencon's once;</l>
                  <l>And much too little of that good I saw</l>

                  <l>Is my report to his great worthiness.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Another of these students at that time</l>
                  <l>Was there with him, if I have heard a truth.</l>
                  <l>Biron they call him; but a merrier man,</l>
                  <l>Within the limit of becoming mirth,</l>
                  <l>I never spent an hour's talk withal:</l>

                  <l>His eye begets occasion for his wit;</l>
                  <l>For every object that the one doth catch</l>
                  <l>The other turns to a mirth-moving jest,</l>
                  <l>Which his fair tongue, conceit's expositor,</l>
                  <l>Delivers in such apt and gracious words</l>
                  <l>That aged ears play truant at his tales</l>
                  <l>And younger hearings are quite ravished;</l>
                  <l>So sweet and voluble is his discourse.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>God bless my ladies! are they all in love,</l>
                  <l>That every one her own hath garnished</l>
                  <l>With such bedecking ornaments of praise?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes Boyet.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Re-enter Boyet</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Now, what admittance, lord?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Navarre had notice of your fair approach;</l>

                  <l>And he and his competitors in oath</l>
                  <l>Were all address'd to meet you, gentle lady,</l>
                  <l>Before I came. Marry, thus much I have learnt:</l>
                  <l>He rather means to lodge you in the field,</l>
                  <l>Like one that comes here to besiege his court,</l>
                  <l>Than seek a dispensation for his oath,</l>
                  <l>To let you enter his unpeopled house.</l>
                  <l>Here comes Navarre.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Ferdinand, Longaville, Dumain, Biron, and
                  Attendants</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Fair Princess, welcome to the court of Navarre.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>'Fair' I give you back again; and 'welcome' I have</l>

                  <l>not yet: the roof of this court is too high to be</l>
                  <l>yours; and welcome to the wide fields too base to be
                     mine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>You shall be welcome, madam, to my court.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>I will be welcome, then: conduct me thither.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Hear me, dear lady; I have sworn an oath.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Our Lady help my lord! he'll be forsworn.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Not for the world, fair madam, by my will.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Why, will shall break it; will and nothing else.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Your ladyship is ignorant what it is.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Were my lord so, his ignorance were wise,</l>
                  <l>Where now his knowledge must prove ignorance.</l>
                  <l>I hear your grace hath sworn out house-keeping:</l>
                  <l>Tis deadly sin to keep that oath, my lord,</l>
                  <l>And sin to break it.</l>
                  <l>But pardon me. I am too sudden-bold:</l>

                  <l>To teach a teacher ill beseemeth me.</l>
                  <l>Vouchsafe to read the purpose of my coming,</l>
                  <l>And suddenly resolve me in my suit.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I will, if suddenly I may.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>You will the sooner, that I were away;</l>
                  <l>For you'll prove perjured if you make me stay.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Did not I dance with you in Brabant once?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Did not I dance with you in Brabant once?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I know you did.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>How needless was it then to ask the question!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>You must not be so quick.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis 'long of you that spur me with such questions.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Your wit's too hot, it speeds too fast, 'twill tire.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Not till it leave the rider in the mire.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>What time o' day?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>The hour that fools should ask.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Now fair befall your mask!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Fair fall the face it covers!</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>And send you many lovers!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Amen, so you be none.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, then will I be gone.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, your father here doth intimate</l>
                  <l>The payment of a hundred thousand crowns;</l>
                  <l>Being but the one half of an entire sum</l>
                  <l>Disbursed by my father in his wars.</l>

                  <l>But say that he or we, as neither have,</l>
                  <l>Received that sum, yet there remains unpaid</l>
                  <l>A hundred thousand more; in surety of the which,</l>
                  <l>One part of Aquitaine is bound to us,</l>
                  <l>Although not valued to the money's worth.</l>
                  <l>If then the king your father will restore</l>
                  <l>But that one half which is unsatisfied,</l>
                  <l>We will give up our right in Aquitaine,</l>
                  <l>And hold fair friendship with his majesty.</l>

                  <l>But that, it seems, he little purposeth,</l>
                  <l>For here he doth demand to have repaid</l>
                  <l>A hundred thousand crowns; and not demands,</l>
                  <l>On payment of a hundred thousand crowns,</l>
                  <l>To have his title live in Aquitaine;</l>
                  <l>Which we much rather had depart withal</l>
                  <l>And have the money by our father lent</l>
                  <l>Than Aquitaine so gelded as it is.</l>
                  <l>Dear Princess, were not his requests so far</l>

                  <l>From reason's yielding, your fair self should make</l>
                  <l>A yielding 'gainst some reason in my breast</l>
                  <l>And go well satisfied to France again.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>You do the king my father too much wrong</l>
                  <l>And wrong the reputation of your name,</l>
                  <l>In so unseeming to confess receipt</l>

                  <l>Of that which hath so faithfully been paid.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>I do protest I never heard of it;</l>
                  <l>And if you prove it, I'll repay it back</l>
                  <l>Or yield up Aquitaine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>We arrest your word.</l>
                  <l>Boyet, you can produce acquittances</l>
                  <l>For such a sum from special officers</l>
                  <l>Of Charles his father.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Satisfy me so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>So please your grace, the packet is not come</l>
                  <l>Where that and other specialties are bound:</l>
                  <l>To-morrow you shall have a sight of them.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>It shall suffice me: at which interview</l>
                  <l>All liberal reason I will yield unto.</l>

                  <l>Meantime receive such welcome at my hand</l>
                  <l>As honour without breach of honour may</l>
                  <l>Make tender of to thy true worthiness:</l>
                  <l>You may not come, fair Princess, in my gates;</l>
                  <l>But here without you shall be so received</l>
                  <l>As you shall deem yourself lodged in my heart,</l>
                  <l>Though so denied fair harbour in my house.</l>
                  <l>Your own good thoughts excuse me, and farewell:</l>
                  <l>To-morrow shall we visit you again.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet health and fair desires consort your grace!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Thy own wish wish I thee in every place!</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Lady, I will commend you to mine own heart.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Pray you, do my commendations; I would be glad to see
                     it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I would you heard it groan.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Is the fool sick?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Sick at the heart.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Alack, let it blood.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Would that do it good?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>My physic says 'ay.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Will you prick't with your eye?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>

                  <l>No point, with my knife.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Now, God save thy life!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>And yours from long living!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot stay thanksgiving.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Retiring</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I pray you, a word: what lady is that same?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>The heir of Alencon, Katherine her name.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>A gallant lady. Monsieur, fare you well.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>I beseech you a word: what is she in the white?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>A woman sometimes, an you saw her in the light.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Perchance light in the light. I desire her name.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>She hath but one for herself; to desire that were a
                     shame.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>

                  <l>Pray you, sir, whose daughter?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Her mother's, I have heard.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>God's blessing on your beard!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Good sir, be not offended.</l>
                  <l>She is an heir of Falconbridge.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, my choler is ended.</l>
                  <l>She is a most sweet lady.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Not unlike, sir, that may be.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit Longaville</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>What's her name in the cap?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Rosaline, by good hap.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Is she wedded or no?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>To her will, sir, or so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>You are welcome, sir: adieu.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell to me, sir, and welcome to you.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Exit Biron</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>That last is Biron, the merry madcap lord:</l>
                  <l>Not a word with him but a jest.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>And every jest but a word.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>It was well done of you to take him at his word.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>I was as willing to grapple as he was to board.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Two hot sheeps, marry.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>And wherefore not ships?</l>
                  <l>No sheep, sweet lamb, unless we feed on your lips.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>You sheep, and I pasture: shall that finish the jest?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>So you grant pasture for me.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Offering to kiss her</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Not so, gentle beast:</l>
                  <l>My lips are no common, though several they be.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Belonging to whom?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>To my fortunes and me.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Good wits will be jangling; but, gentles, agree:</l>
                  <l>This civil war of wits were much better used</l>
                  <l>On Navarre and his book-men; for here 'tis abused.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>If my observation, which very seldom lies,</l>
                  <l>By the heart's still rhetoric disclosed with eyes,</l>
                  <l>Deceive me not now, Navarre is infected.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>With what?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>With that which we lovers entitle affected.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Your reason?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Why, all his behaviors did make their retire</l>
                  <l>To the court of his eye, peeping thorough desire:</l>
                  <l>His heart, like an agate, with your print impress'd,</l>
                  <l>Proud with his form, in his eye pride express'd:</l>
                  <l>His tongue, all impatient to speak and not see,</l>
                  <l>Did stumble with haste in his eyesight to be;</l>
                  <l>All senses to that sense did make their repair,</l>
                  <l>To feel only looking on fairest of fair:</l>

                  <l>Methought all his senses were lock'd in his eye,</l>
                  <l>As jewels in crystal for some prince to buy;</l>
                  <l>Who, tendering their own worth from where they were
                     glass'd,</l>
                  <l>Did point you to buy them, along as you pass'd:</l>
                  <l>His face's own margent did quote such amazes</l>
                  <l>That all eyes saw his eyes enchanted with gazes.</l>
                  <l>I'll give you Aquitaine and all that is his,</l>
                  <l>An you give him for my sake but one loving kiss.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Come to our pavilion: Boyet is disposed.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>But to speak that in words which his eye hath</l>
                  <l>disclosed.</l>
                  <l>I only have made a mouth of his eye,</l>

                  <l>By adding a tongue which I know will not lie.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art an old love-monger and speakest skilfully.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>He is Cupid's grandfather and learns news of him.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Then was Venus like her mother, for her father is but
                     grim.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Do you hear, my mad wenches?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>

                  <l>No.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>What then, do you see?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, our way to be gone.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>You are too hard for me.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>

         </div>

         <div type="act" n="3">
            <div type="scene" n="1">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter Don Adriano and Moth</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Warble, child; make passionate my sense of hearing.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Singing</stage>Concolinel.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet air! Go, tenderness of years; take this key,</l>
                  <l>give enlargement to the swain, bring him festinately</l>
                  <l>hither: I must employ him in a letter to my love.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Master, will you win your love with a French brawl?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>How meanest thou? brawling in French?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>No, my complete master: but to jig off a tune at</l>
                  <l>the tongue's end, canary to it with your feet, humour</l>
                  <l>it with turning up your eyelids, sigh a note and</l>
                  <l>sing a note, sometime through the throat, as if you</l>
                  <l>swallowed love with singing love, sometime through</l>
                  <l>the nose, as if you snuffed up love by smelling</l>
                  <l>love; with your hat penthouse-like o'er the shop of</l>
                  <l>your eyes; with your arms crossed on your thin-belly</l>
                  <l>doublet like a rabbit on a spit; or your hands in</l>

                  <l>your pocket like a man after the old painting; and</l>
                  <l>keep not too long in one tune, but a snip and away.</l>
                  <l>These are complements, these are humours; these</l>
                  <l>betray nice wenches, that would be betrayed without</l>
                  <l>these; and make them men of note--do you note</l>
                  <l>me?--that most are affected to these.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>How hast thou purchased this experience?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>By my penny of observation.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>But O,--but O,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>'The hobby-horse is forgot.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Callest thou my love 'hobby-horse'?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>No, master; the hobby-horse is but a colt, and your</l>
                  <l>love perhaps a hackney. But have you forgot your love?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Almost I had.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Negligent student! learn her by heart.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>By heart and in heart, boy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>And out of heart, master: all those three I will prove.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>What wilt thou prove?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>A man, if I live; and this, by, in, and without, upon</l>
                  <l>the instant: by heart you love her, because your</l>
                  <l>heart cannot come by her; in heart you love her,</l>
                  <l>because your heart is in love with her; and out of</l>

                  <l>heart you love her, being out of heart that you</l>
                  <l>cannot enjoy her.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I am all these three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>And three times as much more, and yet nothing at</l>

                  <l>all.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Fetch hither the swain: he must carry me a letter.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>A message well sympathized; a horse to be ambassador</l>
                  <l>for an ass.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha! what sayest thou?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Marry, sir, you must send the ass upon the horse,</l>
                  <l>for he is very slow-gaited. But I go.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>The way is but short: away!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>As swift as lead, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>The meaning, pretty ingenious?</l>
                  <l>Is not lead a metal heavy, Dull, and slow?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Minime, honest master; or rather, master, no.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I say lead is slow.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>You are too swift, sir, to say so:</l>
                  <l>Is that lead slow which is fired from a gun?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet smoke of rhetoric!</l>
                  <l>He reputes me a cannon; and the bullet, that's he:</l>

                  <l>I shoot thee at the swain.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Thump then and I flee.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>A most acute juvenal; voluble and free of grace!</l>
                  <l>By thy favour, sweet welkin, I must sigh in thy face:</l>
                  <l>Most rude melancholy, valour gives thee place.</l>
                  <l>My herald is return'd.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Re-enter Moth with Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>A wonder, master! here's a Costard broken in a shin.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Some enigma, some riddle: come, thy l'envoy; begin.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>No enigma, no riddle, no l'envoy; no salve in the</l>
                  <l>mail, sir: O, sir, plantain, a plain plantain! no</l>

                  <l>l'envoy, no l'envoy; no salve, sir, but a plantain!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>By virtue, thou enforcest laughter; thy silly</l>
                  <l>thought my spleen; the heaving of my lungs provokes</l>
                  <l>me to ridiculous smiling. O, pardon me, my stars!</l>
                  <l>Doth the inconsiderate take salve for l'envoy, and</l>
                  <l>the word l'envoy for a salve?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Do the wise think them other? is not l'envoy a salve?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>No, page: it is an epilogue or discourse, to make plain</l>
                  <l>Some obscure precedence that hath tofore been sain.</l>
                  <l>I will example it:</l>

                  <l>The fox, the ape, and the humble-bee,</l>
                  <l>Were still at odds, being but three.</l>
                  <l>There's the moral. Now the l'envoy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>I will add the l'envoy. Say the moral again.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>The fox, the ape, and the humble-bee,</l>
                  <l>Were still at odds, being but three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Until the goose came out of door,</l>
                  <l>And stay'd the odds by adding four.</l>
                  <l>Now will I begin your moral, and do you follow with</l>
                  <l>my l'envoy.</l>

                  <l>The fox, the ape, and the humble-bee,</l>
                  <l>Were still at odds, being but three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Until the goose came out of door,</l>
                  <l>Staying the odds by adding four.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>A good l'envoy, ending in the goose: would you</l>
                  <l>desire more?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>The boy hath sold him a bargain, a goose, that's flat.</l>
                  <l>Sir, your pennyworth is good, an your goose be fat.</l>
                  <l>To sell a bargain well is as cunning as fast and loose:</l>
                  <l>Let me see; a fat l'envoy; ay, that's a fat goose.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Come hither, come hither. How did this argument begin?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>By saying that a Costard was broken in a shin.</l>
                  <l>Then call'd you for the l'envoy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>True, and I for a plantain: thus came your</l>
                  <l>argument in;</l>
                  <l>Then the boy's fat l'envoy, the goose that you bought;</l>
                  <l>And he ended the market.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l>But tell me; how was there a Costard broken in a shin?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>I will tell you sensibly.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Thou hast no feeling of it, Moth: I will speak that
                     l'envoy:</l>
                  <l>I Costard, running out, that was safely within,</l>

                  <l>Fell over the threshold and broke my shin.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>We will talk no more of this matter.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Till there be more matter in the shin.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sirrah Costard, I will enfranchise thee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>O, marry me to one Frances: I smell some l'envoy,</l>
                  <l>some goose, in this.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>By my sweet soul, I mean setting thee at liberty,</l>
                  <l>enfreedoming thy person; thou wert immured,</l>
                  <l>restrained, captivated, bound.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>True, true; and now you will be my purgation and let me
                     loose.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I give thee thy liberty, set thee from durance; and,</l>
                  <l>in lieu thereof, impose on thee nothing but this:</l>
                  <l>bear this significant</l>
                  <stage>Giving a letter</stage>
                  <l>to the country maid Jaquenetta:</l>
                  <l>there is remuneration; for the best ward of mine</l>

                  <l>honour is rewarding my dependents. Moth, follow.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Like the sequel, I. Signior Costard, adieu.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>My sweet ounce of man's flesh! my incony Jew!</l>
                  <stage>Exit Moth</stage>
                  <l>Now will I look to his remuneration. Remuneration!</l>
                  <l>O, that's the Latin word for three farthings: three</l>
                  <l>farthings--remuneration.--'What's the price of this</l>
                  <l>inkle?'--'One penny.'--'No, I'll give you a</l>
                  <l>remuneration:' why, it carries it. Remuneration!</l>
                  <l>why, it is a fairer name than French crown. I will</l>
                  <l>never buy and sell out of this word.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Biron</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>O, my good knave Costard! exceedingly well met.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Pray you, sir, how much carnation ribbon may a man</l>

                  <l>buy for a remuneration?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>What is a remuneration?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Marry, sir, halfpenny farthing.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Why, then, three-farthing worth of silk.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I thank your worship: God be wi' you!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Stay, slave; I must employ thee:</l>
                  <l>As thou wilt win my favour, good my knave,</l>
                  <l>Do one thing for me that I shall entreat.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>When would you have it done, sir?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>This afternoon.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Well, I will do it, sir: fare you well.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Thou knowest not what it is.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I shall know, sir, when I have done it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Why, villain, thou must know first.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>I will come to your worship to-morrow morning.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>It must be done this afternoon.</l>
                  <l>Hark, slave, it is but this:</l>
                  <l>The Princess comes to hunt here in the park,</l>
                  <l>And in her train there is a gentle lady;</l>
                  <l>When tongues speak sweetly, then they name her name,</l>

                  <l>And Rosaline they call her: ask for her;</l>
                  <l>And to her white hand see thou do commend</l>
                  <l>This seal'd-up counsel. There's thy guerdon; go.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Giving him a shilling</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Gardon, O sweet gardon! better than remuneration,</l>

                  <l>a'leven-pence farthing better: most sweet gardon! I</l>
                  <l>will do it sir, in print. Gardon! Remuneration!</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>And I, forsooth, in love! I, that have been love's
                     whip;</l>
                  <l>A very beadle to a humorous sigh;</l>

                  <l>A critic, nay, a night-watch constable;</l>
                  <l>A domineering pedant o'er the boy;</l>
                  <l>Than whom no mortal so magnificent!</l>
                  <l>This whimpled, whining, purblind, wayward boy;</l>
                  <l>This senior-junior, giant-dwarf, Dan Cupid;</l>
                  <l>Regent of love-rhymes, lord of folded arms,</l>
                  <l>The anointed sovereign of sighs and groans,</l>
                  <l>Liege of all loiterers and malcontents,</l>
                  <l>Dread prince of plackets, king of codpieces,</l>

                  <l>Sole imperator and great general</l>
                  <l>Of trotting 'paritors:--O my little heart:--</l>
                  <l>And I to be a corporal of his field,</l>
                  <l>And wear his colours like a tumbler's hoop!</l>
                  <l>What, I! I love! I sue! I seek a wife!</l>
                  <l>A woman, that is like a German clock,</l>
                  <l>Still a-repairing, ever out of frame,</l>
                  <l>And never going aright, being a watch,</l>
                  <l>But being watch'd that it may still go right!</l>

                  <l>Nay, to be perjured, which is worst of all;</l>
                  <l>And, among three, to love the worst of all;</l>
                  <l>A wightly wanton with a velvet brow,</l>
                  <l>With two pitch-balls stuck in her face for eyes;</l>
                  <l>Ay, and by heaven, one that will do the deed</l>
                  <l>Though Argus were her eunuch and her guard:</l>
                  <l>And I to sigh for her! to watch for her!</l>
                  <l>To pray for her! Go to; it is a plague</l>
                  <l>That Cupid will impose for my neglect</l>

                  <l>Of his almighty dreadful little might.</l>
                  <l>Well, I will love, write, sigh, pray, sue and groan:</l>
                  <l>Some men must love my lady and some Joan.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Exit</stage>
            </div>

         </div>

         <div type="act" n="4">
            <div type="scene" n="1">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter the Princess, and her train, a forester, Boyet,
                  Rosaline, Maria, and Katherine</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Was that the king, that spurred his horse so hard</l>
                  <l>Against the steep uprising of the hill?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>I know not; but I think it was not he.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Whoe'er a' was, a' show'd a mounting mind.</l>
                  <l>Well, lords, to-day we shall have our dispatch:</l>
                  <l>On Saturday we will return to France.</l>
                  <l>Then, forester, my friend, where is the bush</l>
                  <l>That we must stand and play the murderer in?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Forester</speaker>
                  <l>Hereby, upon the edge of yonder coppice;</l>
                  <l>A stand where you may make the fairest shoot.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>I thank my beauty, I am fair that shoot,</l>
                  <l>And thereupon thou speak'st the fairest shoot.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Forester</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon me, madam, for I meant not so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>What, what? first praise me and again say no?</l>
                  <l>O short-lived pride! Not fair? alack for woe!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Forester</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, madam, fair.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, never paint me now:</l>
                  <l>Where fair is not, praise cannot mend the brow.</l>
                  <l>Here, good my glass, take this for telling true:</l>

                  <l>Fair payment for foul words is more than due.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Forester</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but fair is that which you inherit.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>See see, my beauty will be saved by merit!</l>
                  <l>O heresy in fair, fit for these days!</l>

                  <l>A giving hand, though foul, shall have fair praise.</l>
                  <l>But come, the bow: now mercy goes to kill,</l>
                  <l>And shooting well is then accounted ill.</l>
                  <l>Thus will I save my credit in the shoot:</l>
                  <l>Not wounding, pity would not let me do't;</l>
                  <l>If wounding, then it was to show my skill,</l>
                  <l>That more for praise than purpose meant to kill.</l>
                  <l>And out of question so it is sometimes,</l>
                  <l>Glory grows guilty of detested crimes,</l>

                  <l>When, for fame's sake, for praise, an outward part,</l>
                  <l>We bend to that the working of the heart;</l>
                  <l>As I for praise alone now seek to spill</l>
                  <l>The poor deer's blood, that my heart means no ill.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Do not curst wives hold that self-sovereignty</l>
                  <l>Only for praise sake, when they strive to be</l>

                  <l>Lords o'er their lords?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Only for praise: and praise we may afford</l>
                  <l>To any lady that subdues a lord.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes a member of the commonwealth.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>God dig-you-den all! Pray you, which is the head lady?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Thou shalt know her, fellow, by the rest that have no
                     heads.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Which is the greatest lady, the highest?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>The thickest and the tallest.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>The thickest and the tallest! it is so; truth is truth.</l>
                  <l>An your waist, mistress, were as slender as my wit,</l>
                  <l>One o' these maids' girdles for your waist should be
                     fit.</l>
                  <l>Are not you the chief woman? you are the thickest here.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>What's your will, sir? what's your will?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I have a letter from Monsieur Biron to one Lady
                     Rosaline.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>O, thy letter, thy letter! he's a good friend of mine:</l>
                  <l>Stand aside, good bearer. Boyet, you can carve;</l>
                  <l>Break up this capon.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>I am bound to serve.</l>
                  <l>This letter is mistook, it importeth none here;</l>
                  <l>It is writ to Jaquenetta.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>We will read it, I swear.</l>

                  <l>Break the neck of the wax, and every one give ear.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Reads</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>'By heaven, that thou art fair, is most infallible;</l>
                  <l>true, that thou art beauteous; truth itself, that</l>
                  <l>thou art lovely. More fairer than fair, beautiful</l>

                  <l>than beauteous, truer than truth itself, have</l>
                  <l>commiseration on thy heroical vassal! The</l>
                  <l>magnanimous and most illustrate king Cophetua set</l>
                  <l>eye upon the pernicious and indubitate beggar</l>
                  <l>Zenelophon; and he it was that might rightly say,</l>
                  <l>Veni, vidi, vici; which to annothanize in the</l>
                  <l>vulgar,--O base and obscure vulgar!--videlicet, He</l>
                  <l>came, saw, and overcame: he came, one; saw two;</l>
                  <l>overcame, three. Who came? the king: why did he</l>

                  <l>come? to see: why did he see? to overcome: to</l>
                  <l>whom came he? to the beggar: what saw he? the</l>
                  <l>beggar: who overcame he? the beggar. The</l>
                  <l>conclusion is victory: on whose side? the king's.</l>
                  <l>The captive is enriched: on whose side? the</l>
                  <l>beggar's. The catastrophe is a nuptial: on whose</l>
                  <l>side? the king's: no, on both in one, or one in</l>
                  <l>both. I am the king; for so stands the comparison:</l>
                  <l>thou the beggar; for so witnesseth thy lowliness.</l>

                  <l>Shall I command thy love? I may: shall I enforce</l>
                  <l>thy love? I could: shall I entreat thy love? I</l>
                  <l>will. What shalt thou exchange for rags? robes;</l>
                  <l>for tittles? titles; for thyself? me. Thus,</l>
                  <l>expecting thy reply, I profane my lips on thy foot,</l>
                  <l>my eyes on thy picture. and my heart on thy every</l>
                  <l>part. Thine, in the dearest design of industry,</l>
                  <l>Don Adriano.'</l>
                  <l>Thus dost thou hear the Nemean lion roar</l>

                  <l>'Gainst thee, thou lamb, that standest as his prey.</l>
                  <l>Submissive fall his princely feet before,</l>
                  <l>And he from forage will incline to play:</l>
                  <l>But if thou strive, poor soul, what art thou then?</l>
                  <l>Food for his rage, repasture for his den.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>What plume of feathers is he that indited this letter?</l>

                  <l>What vane? what weathercock? did you ever hear better?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>I am much deceived but I remember the style.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Else your memory is bad, going o'er it erewhile.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>This Armado is a Spaniard, that keeps here in court;</l>
                  <l>A phantasime, a Monarcho, and one that makes sport</l>
                  <l>To the prince and his bookmates.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Thou fellow, a word:</l>

                  <l>Who gave thee this letter?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I told you; my lord.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>To whom shouldst thou give it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>From my lord to my lady.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>From which lord to which lady?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>From my lord Biron, a good master of mine,</l>
                  <l>To a lady of France that he call'd Rosaline.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Thou hast mistaken his letter. Come, lords, away.</l>
                  <stage>To Rosaline</stage>
                  <l>Here, sweet, put up this: 'twill be thine another day.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Exeunt Princess and train</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Who is the suitor? who is the suitor?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I teach you to know?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, my continent of beauty.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Why, she that bears the bow.</l>
                  <l>Finely put off!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>My lady goes to kill horns; but, if thou marry,</l>
                  <l>Hang me by the neck, if horns that year miscarry.</l>
                  <l>Finely put on!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Well, then, I am the shooter.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>And who is your deer?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>If we choose by the horns, yourself come not near.</l>
                  <l>Finely put on, indeed!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>You still wrangle with her, Boyet, and she strikes</l>
                  <l>at the brow.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>But she herself is hit lower: have I hit her now?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I come upon thee with an old saying, that was</l>
                  <l>a man when King Pepin of France was a little boy, as</l>
                  <l>touching the hit it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>So I may answer thee with one as old, that was a</l>
                  <l>woman when Queen Guinover of Britain was a little</l>

                  <l>wench, as touching the hit it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Thou canst not hit it, hit it, hit it,</l>
                  <l>Thou canst not hit it, my good man.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>An I cannot, cannot, cannot,</l>

                  <l>An I cannot, another can.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Rosaline and Katherine</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>By my troth, most pleasant: how both did fit it!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>

                  <l>A mark marvellous well shot, for they both did hit it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>A mark! O, mark but that mark! A mark, says my lady!</l>
                  <l>Let the mark have a prick in't, to mete at, if it may
                     be.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Wide o' the bow hand! i' faith, your hand is out.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed, a' must shoot nearer, or he'll ne'er hit the
                     clout.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>An if my hand be out, then belike your hand is in.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Then will she get the upshoot by cleaving the pin.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, you talk greasily; your lips grow foul.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>She's too hard for you at pricks, sir: challenge her to
                     bowl.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>I fear too much rubbing. Good night, my good owl.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Boyet and Maria</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>By my soul, a swain! a most simple clown!</l>

                  <l>Lord, Lord, how the ladies and I have put him down!</l>
                  <l>O' my troth, most sweet jests! most incony</l>
                  <l>vulgar wit!</l>
                  <l>When it comes so smoothly off, so obscenely, as it</l>
                  <l>were, so fit.</l>
                  <l>Armado o' th' one side,--O, a most dainty man!</l>
                  <l>To see him walk before a lady and to bear her fan!</l>
                  <l>To see him kiss his hand! and how most sweetly a'</l>
                  <l>will swear!</l>

                  <l>And his page o' t' other side, that handful of wit!</l>
                  <l>Ah, heavens, it is a most pathetical nit!</l>
                  <l>Sola, sola!</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Shout within</stage>
               <stage>Exit Costard, running</stage>
            </div>

            <div type="scene" n="2">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter Holofernes, Sir Nathaniel, and Dull</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Very reverend sport, truly; and done in the testimony</l>
                  <l>of a good conscience.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>The deer was, as you know, sanguis, in blood; ripe</l>
                  <l>as the pomewater, who now hangeth like a jewel in</l>

                  <l>the ear of caelo, the sky, the welkin, the heaven;</l>
                  <l>and anon falleth like a crab on the face of terra,</l>
                  <l>the soil, the land, the earth.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Truly, Master Holofernes, the epithets are sweetly</l>
                  <l>varied, like a scholar at the least: but, sir, I</l>
                  <l>assure ye, it was a buck of the first head.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Sir Nathaniel, haud credo.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas not a haud credo; 'twas a pricket.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Most barbarous intimation! yet a kind of</l>
                  <l>insinuation, as it were, in via, in way, of</l>
                  <l>explication; facere, as it were, replication, or</l>
                  <l>rather, ostentare, to show, as it were, his</l>
                  <l>inclination, after his undressed, unpolished,</l>
                  <l>uneducated, unpruned, untrained, or rather,</l>
                  <l>unlettered, or ratherest, unconfirmed fashion, to</l>
                  <l>insert again my haud credo for a deer.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>I said the deer was not a haud credo; twas a pricket.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Twice-sod simplicity, his coctus!</l>
                  <l>O thou monster Ignorance, how deformed dost thou look!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, he hath never fed of the dainties that are bred</l>
                  <l>in a book; he hath not eat paper, as it were; he</l>
                  <l>hath not drunk ink: his intellect is not</l>
                  <l>replenished; he is only an animal, only sensible in</l>
                  <l>the duller parts:</l>
                  <l>And such barren plants are set before us, that we</l>
                  <l>thankful should be,</l>

                  <l>Which we of taste and feeling are, for those parts that</l>
                  <l>do fructify in us more than he.</l>
                  <l>For as it would ill become me to be vain, indiscreet, or a
                     fool,</l>
                  <l>So were there a patch set on learning, to see him in a
                     school:</l>
                  <l>But omne bene, say I; being of an old father's mind,</l>
                  <l>Many can brook the weather that love not the wind.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>

                  <l>You two are book-men: can you tell me by your wit</l>
                  <l>What was a month old at Cain's birth, that's not five</l>
                  <l>weeks old as yet?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Dictynna, goodman Dull; Dictynna, goodman Dull.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>

                  <l>What is Dictynna?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>A title to Phoebe, to Luna, to the moon.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>The moon was a month old when Adam was no more,</l>
                  <l>And raught not to five weeks when he came to</l>

                  <l>five-score.</l>
                  <l>The allusion holds in the exchange.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true indeed; the collusion holds in the exchange.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>God comfort thy capacity! I say, the allusion holds</l>

                  <l>in the exchange.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>And I say, the pollusion holds in the exchange; for</l>
                  <l>the moon is never but a month old: and I say beside</l>
                  <l>that, 'twas a pricket that the Princess killed.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>

                  <l>Sir Nathaniel, will you hear an extemporal epitaph</l>
                  <l>on the death of the deer? And, to humour the</l>
                  <l>ignorant, call I the deer the Princess killed a
                     pricket.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Perge, good Master Holofernes, perge; so it shall</l>
                  <l>please you to abrogate scurrility.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>I will something affect the letter, for it argues
                     facility.</l>
                  <l>The preyful Princess pierced and prick'd a pretty</l>
                  <l>pleasing pricket;</l>
                  <l>Some say a sore; but not a sore, till now made</l>
                  <l>sore with shooting.</l>
                  <l>The dogs did yell: put L to sore, then sorel jumps</l>
                  <l>from thicket;</l>

                  <l>Or pricket sore, or else sorel; the people fall
                     a-hooting.</l>
                  <l>If sore be sore, then L to sore makes fifty sores</l>
                  <l>one sorel.</l>
                  <l>Of one sore I an hundred make by adding but one more L.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>A rare talent!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside</stage> If a talent be a claw, look how he
                     claws</l>
                  <l>him with a talent.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>This is a gift that I have, simple, simple; a</l>
                  <l>foolish extravagant spirit, full of forms, figures,</l>

                  <l>shapes, objects, ideas, apprehensions, motions,</l>
                  <l>revolutions: these are begot in the ventricle of</l>
                  <l>memory, nourished in the womb of pia mater, and</l>
                  <l>delivered upon the mellowing of occasion. But the</l>
                  <l>gift is good in those in whom it is acute, and I am</l>
                  <l>thankful for it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>

                  <l>Sir, I praise the Lord for you; and so may my</l>
                  <l>parishioners; for their sons are well tutored by</l>
                  <l>you, and their daughters profit very greatly under</l>
                  <l>you: you are a good member of the commonwealth.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Mehercle, if their sons be ingenuous, they shall</l>
                  <l>want no instruction; if their daughters be capable,</l>

                  <l>I will put it to them: but vir sapit qui pauca</l>
                  <l>loquitur; a soul feminine saluteth us.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Jaquenetta and Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>God give you good morrow, master Parson.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Master Parson, quasi pers-on. An if one should be</l>
                  <l>pierced, which is the one?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Marry, master schoolmaster, he that is likest to a
                     hogshead.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Piercing a hogshead! a good lustre of conceit in a</l>
                  <l>tuft of earth; fire enough for a flint, pearl enough</l>
                  <l>for a swine: 'tis pretty; it is well.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Good master Parson, be so good as read me this</l>
                  <l>letter: it was given me by Costard, and sent me</l>

                  <l>from Don Armado: I beseech you, read it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Fauste, precor gelida quando pecus omne sub umbra</l>
                  <l>Ruminat,--and so forth. Ah, good old Mantuan! I</l>
                  <l>may speak of thee as the traveller doth of Venice;</l>
                  <l>Venetia, Venetia,</l>
                  <l>Chi non ti vede non ti pretia.</l>

                  <l>Old Mantuan, old Mantuan! who understandeth thee</l>
                  <l>not, loves thee not. Ut, re, sol, la, mi, fa.</l>
                  <l>Under pardon, sir, what are the contents? or rather,</l>
                  <l>as Horace says in his--What, my soul, verses?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, sir, and very learned.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Let me hear a staff, a stanze, a verse; lege, domine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Reads</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>If love make me forsworn, how shall I swear to love?</l>
                  <l>Ah, never faith could hold, if not to beauty vow'd!</l>
                  <l>Though to myself forsworn, to thee I'll faithful prove:</l>

                  <l>Those thoughts to me were oaks, to thee like</l>
                  <l>osiers bow'd.</l>
                  <l>Study his bias leaves and makes his book thine eyes,</l>
                  <l>Where all those pleasures live that art would</l>
                  <l>comprehend:</l>
                  <l>If knowledge be the mark, to know thee shall suffice;</l>
                  <l>Well learned is that tongue that well can thee commend,</l>
                  <l>All ignorant that soul that sees thee without wonder;</l>
                  <l>Which is to me some praise that I thy parts admire:</l>

                  <l>Thy eye Jove's lightning bears, thy voice his dreadful
                     thunder,</l>
                  <l>Which not to anger bent, is music and sweet fire.</l>
                  <l>Celestial as thou art, O, pardon, love, this wrong,</l>
                  <l>That sings heaven's praise with such an earthly tongue.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>You find not the apostraphas, and so miss the</l>
                  <l>accent: let me supervise the canzonet. Here are</l>

                  <l>only numbers ratified; but, for the elegancy,</l>
                  <l>facility, and golden cadence of poesy, caret.</l>
                  <l>Ovidius Naso was the man: and why, indeed, Naso,</l>
                  <l>but for smelling out the odouriferous flowers of</l>
                  <l>fancy, the jerks of invention? Imitari is nothing:</l>
                  <l>so doth the hound his master, the ape his keeper,</l>
                  <l>the tired horse his rider. But, damosella virgin,</l>
                  <l>was this directed to you?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, sir, from one Monsieur Biron, one of the strange</l>
                  <l>queen's lords.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>I will overglance the superscript: 'To the</l>
                  <l>snow-white hand of the most beauteous Lady</l>

                  <l>Rosaline.' I will look again on the intellect of</l>
                  <l>the letter, for the nomination of the party writing</l>
                  <l>to the person written unto: 'Your ladyship's in all</l>
                  <l>desired employment, Biron.' Sir Nathaniel, this</l>
                  <l>Biron is one of the votaries with the king; and here</l>
                  <l>he hath framed a letter to a sequent of the stranger</l>
                  <l>queen's, which accidentally, or by the way of</l>
                  <l>progression, hath miscarried. Trip and go, my</l>
                  <l>sweet; deliver this paper into the royal hand of the</l>

                  <l>king: it may concern much. Stay not thy</l>
                  <l>compliment; I forgive thy duty; adieu.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Good Costard, go with me. Sir, God save your life!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Have with thee, my girl.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Costard and Jaquenetta</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you have done this in the fear of God, very</l>
                  <l>religiously; and, as a certain father saith,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>

                  <l>Sir tell me not of the father; I do fear colourable</l>
                  <l>colours. But to return to the verses: did they</l>
                  <l>please you, Sir Nathaniel?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Marvellous well for the pen.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>

                  <l>I do dine to-day at the father's of a certain pupil</l>
                  <l>of mine; where, if, before repast, it shall please</l>
                  <l>you to gratify the table with a grace, I will, on my</l>
                  <l>privilege I have with the parents of the foresaid</l>
                  <l>child or pupil, undertake your ben venuto; where I</l>
                  <l>will prove those verses to be very unlearned,</l>
                  <l>neither savouring of poetry, wit, nor invention: I</l>
                  <l>beseech your society.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>And thank you too; for society, saith the text, is</l>
                  <l>the happiness of life.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>And, certes, the text most infallibly concludes it.</l>
                  <stage>To Dull</stage>

                  <l>Sir, I do invite you too; you shall not</l>
                  <l>say me nay: pauca verba. Away! the gentles are at</l>
                  <l>their game, and we will to our recreation.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>

            <div type="scene" n="3">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter Biron, with a paper</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>The king he is hunting the deer; I am coursing</l>
                  <l>myself: they have pitched a toil; I am toiling in</l>
                  <l>a pitch,--pitch that defiles: defile! a foul</l>
                  <l>word. Well, set thee down, sorrow! for so they say</l>
                  <l>the fool said, and so say I, and I the fool: well</l>
                  <l>proved, wit! By the Lord, this love is as mad as</l>
                  <l>Ajax: it kills sheep; it kills me, I a sheep:</l>
                  <l>well proved again o' my side! I will not love: if</l>
                  <l>I do, hang me; i' faith, I will not. O, but her</l>
                  <l>eye,--by this light, but for her eye, I would not</l>
                  <l>love her; yes, for her two eyes. Well, I do nothing</l>
                  <l>in the world but lie, and lie in my throat. By</l>
                  <l>heaven, I do love: and it hath taught me to rhyme</l>
                  <l>and to be melancholy; and here is part of my rhyme,</l>
                  <l>and here my melancholy. Well, she hath one o' my</l>
                  <l>sonnets already: the clown bore it, the fool sent</l>
                  <l>it, and the lady hath it: sweet clown, sweeter</l>
                  <l>fool, sweetest lady! By the world, I would not care</l>
                  <l>a pin, if the other three were in. Here comes one</l>
                  <l>with a paper: God give him grace to groan!</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Stands aside</stage>
               <stage>Enter Ferdinand, with a paper</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>Ay me!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside</stage>Shot, by heaven! Proceed, sweet
                     Cupid:</l>
                  <l>thou hast thumped him with thy bird-bolt under the</l>
                  <l>left pap. In faith, secrets!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <stage>Reads</stage>
                  
                     <l>So sweet a kiss the golden sun gives not</l>
                     <l>To those fresh morning drops upon the rose,</l>
                     <l>As thy eye-beams, when their fresh rays have smote</l>
                     <l>The night of dew that on my cheeks down flows:</l>
                     <l>Nor shines the silver moon one half so bright</l>
                     <l>Through the transparent bosom of the deep,</l>
                     <l>As doth thy face through tears of mine give light;</l>
                     <l>Thou shinest in every tear that I do weep:</l>
                     <l>No drop but as a coach doth carry thee;</l>
                     <l>So ridest thou triumphing in my woe.</l>
                     <l>Do but behold the tears that swell in me,</l>
                     <l>And they thy glory through my grief will show:</l>
                     <l>But do not love thyself; then thou wilt keep</l>
                     <l>My tears for glasses, and still make me weep.</l>
                     <l>O queen of queens! how far dost thou excel,</l>
                     <l>No thought can think, nor tongue of mortal tell.</l>
                  

                  <l>How shall she know my griefs? I'll drop the paper:</l>
                  <l>Sweet leaves, shade folly. Who is he comes here?</l>
                  <stage>Steps aside</stage>
                  <l>What, Longaville! and reading! listen, ear.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Now, in thy likeness, one more fool appear!</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Longaville, with a paper</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Ay me, I am forsworn!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Why, he comes in like a perjure, wearing papers.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>In love, I hope: sweet fellowship in shame!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>One drunkard loves another of the name.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Am I the first that have been perjured so?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I could put thee in comfort. Not by two that I know:</l>
                  <l>Thou makest the triumviry, the corner-cap of society,</l>
                  <l>The shape of Love's Tyburn that hangs up simplicity.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>I fear these stubborn lines lack power to move:</l>
                  <l>O sweet Maria, empress of my love!</l>
                  <l>These numbers will I tear, and write in prose.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>O, rhymes are guards on wanton Cupid's hose:</l>
                  <l>Disfigure not his slop.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>This same shall go.</l>
                  <stage>Reads</stage>
                  <l>Did not the heavenly rhetoric of thine eye,</l>
                  <l>'Gainst whom the world cannot hold argument,</l>
                  <l>Persuade my heart to this false perjury?</l>
                  <l>Vows for thee broke deserve not punishment.</l>

                  <l>A woman I forswore; but I will prove,</l>
                  <l>Thou being a goddess, I forswore not thee:</l>
                  <l>My vow was earthly, thou a heavenly love;</l>
                  <l>Thy grace being gain'd cures all disgrace in me.</l>
                  <l>Vows are but breath, and breath a vapour is:</l>
                  <l>Then thou, fair sun, which on my earth dost shine,</l>
                  <l>Exhalest this vapour-vow; in thee it is:</l>
                  <l>If broken then, it is no fault of mine:</l>
                  <l>If by me broke, what fool is not so wise</l>

                  <l>To lose an oath to win a paradise?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>This is the liver-vein, which makes flesh a deity,</l>
                  <l>A green goose a goddess: pure, pure idolatry.</l>
                  <l>God amend us, God amend! we are much out o' the way.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>

                  <l>By whom shall I send this?--Company! stay.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Steps aside</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>All hid, all hid; an old infant play.</l>
                  <l>Like a demigod here sit I in the sky.</l>
                  <l>And wretched fools' secrets heedfully o'ereye.</l>

                  <l>More sacks to the mill! O heavens, I have my wish!</l>
                  <stage>Enter Dumain, with a paper</stage>
                  <l>Dumain transform'd! four woodcocks in a dish!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>O most divine Kate!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>O most profane coxcomb!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>By heaven, the wonder in a mortal eye!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>By earth, she is not, corporal, there you lie.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Her amber hair for foul hath amber quoted.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>An amber-colour'd raven was well noted.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>

                  <l>As upright as the cedar.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Stoop, I say;</l>
                  <l>Her shoulder is with child.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>As fair as day.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, as some days; but then no sun must shine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>O that I had my wish!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>And I had mine!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>And I mine too, good Lord!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Amen, so I had mine: is not that a good word?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>I would forget her; but a fever she</l>
                  <l>Reigns in my blood and will remember'd be.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>A fever in your blood! why, then incision</l>
                  <l>Would let her out in saucers: sweet misprision!</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Once more I'll read the ode that I have writ.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Once more I'll mark how love can vary wit.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Reads</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>On a day--alack the day!--</l>
                  <l>Love, whose month is ever May,</l>
                  <l>Spied a blossom passing fair</l>
                  <l>Playing in the wanton air:</l>
                  <l>Through the velvet leaves the wind,</l>
                  <l>All unseen, can passage find;</l>
                  <l>That the lover, sick to death,</l>

                  <l>Wish himself the heaven's breath.</l>
                  <l>Air, quoth he, thy cheeks may blow;</l>
                  <l>Air, would I might triumph so!</l>
                  <l>But, alack, my hand is sworn</l>
                  <l>Ne'er to pluck thee from thy thorn;</l>
                  <l>Vow, alack, for youth unmeet,</l>
                  <l>Youth so apt to pluck a sweet!</l>
                  <l>Do not call it sin in me,</l>
                  <l>That I am forsworn for thee;</l>

                  <l>Thou for whom Jove would swear</l>
                  <l>Juno but an Ethiope were;</l>
                  <l>And deny himself for Jove,</l>
                  <l>Turning mortal for thy love.</l>
                  <l>This will I send, and something else more plain,</l>
                  <l>That shall express my true love's fasting pain.</l>
                  <l>O, would the king, Biron, and Longaville,</l>
                  <l>Were lovers too! Ill, to example ill,</l>
                  <l>Would from my forehead wipe a perjured note;</l>

                  <l>For none offend where all alike do dote.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Advancing</stage> Dumain, thy love is far from
                     charity.</l>
                  <l>You may look pale, but I should blush, I know,</l>
                  <l>To be o'erheard and taken napping so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Advancing</stage> Come, sir, you blush; as his your
                     case is such;</l>
                  <l>You chide at him, offending twice as much;</l>
                  <l>You do not love Maria; Longaville</l>
                  <l>Did never sonnet for her sake compile,</l>
                  <l>Nor never lay his wreathed arms athwart</l>
                  <l>His loving bosom to keep down his heart.</l>

                  <l>I have been closely shrouded in this bush</l>
                  <l>And mark'd you both and for you both did blush:</l>
                  <l>I heard your guilty rhymes, observed your fashion,</l>
                  <l>Saw sighs reek from you, noted well your passion:</l>
                  <l>Ay me! says one; O Jove! the other cries;</l>
                  <l>One, her hairs were gold, crystal the other's eyes:</l>
                  <stage>To Longaville</stage>
                  <l>You would for paradise break faith, and troth;</l>
                  <stage>To Dumain</stage>

                  <l>And Jove, for your love, would infringe an oath.</l>
                  <l>What will Biron say when that he shall hear</l>
                  <l>Faith so infringed, which such zeal did swear?</l>
                  <l>How will he scorn! how will he spend his wit!</l>
                  <l>How will he triumph, leap and laugh at it!</l>
                  <l>For all the wealth that ever I did see,</l>
                  <l>I would not have him know so much by me.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Now step I forth to whip hypocrisy.</l>
                  <stage>Advancing</stage>
                  <l>Ah, good my liege, I pray thee, pardon me!</l>
                  <l>Good heart, what grace hast thou, thus to reprove</l>
                  <l>These worms for loving, that art most in love?</l>
                  <l>Your eyes do make no coaches; in your tears</l>
                  <l>There is no certain Princess that appears;</l>
                  <l>You'll not be perjured, 'tis a hateful thing;</l>

                  <l>Tush, none but minstrels like of sonneting!</l>
                  <l>But are you not ashamed? nay, are you not,</l>
                  <l>All three of you, to be thus much o'ershot?</l>
                  <l>You found his mote; the king your mote did see;</l>
                  <l>But I a beam do find in each of three.</l>
                  <l>O, what a scene of foolery have I seen,</l>
                  <l>Of sighs, of groans, of sorrow and of teen!</l>
                  <l>O me, with what strict patience have I sat,</l>
                  <l>To see a king transformed to a gnat!</l>

                  <l>To see great Hercules whipping a gig,</l>
                  <l>And profound Solomon to tune a jig,</l>
                  <l>And Nestor play at push-pin with the boys,</l>
                  <l>And critic Timon laugh at idle toys!</l>
                  <l>Where lies thy grief, O, tell me, good Dumain?</l>
                  <l>And gentle Longaville, where lies thy pain?</l>
                  <l>And where my liege's? all about the breast:</l>
                  <l>A caudle, ho!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Too bitter is thy jest.</l>
                  <l>Are we betray'd thus to thy over-view?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Not you to me, but I betray'd by you:</l>
                  <l>I, that am honest; I, that hold it sin</l>

                  <l>To break the vow I am engaged in;</l>
                  <l>I am betray'd, by keeping company</l>
                  <l>With men like men of inconstancy.</l>
                  <l>When shall you see me write a thing in rhyme?</l>
                  <l>Or groan for love? or spend a minute's time</l>
                  <l>In pruning me? When shall you hear that I</l>
                  <l>Will praise a hand, a foot, a face, an eye,</l>
                  <l>A gait, a state, a brow, a breast, a waist,</l>
                  <l>A leg, a limb?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Soft! whither away so fast?</l>
                  <l>A true man or a thief that gallops so?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I post from love: good lover, let me go.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Jaquenetta and Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>God bless the king!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What present hast thou there?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Some certain treason.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What makes treason here?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, it makes nothing, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>If it mar nothing neither,</l>
                  <l>The treason and you go in peace away together.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>

                  <l>I beseech your grace, let this letter be read:</l>
                  <l>Our parson misdoubts it; 'twas treason, he said.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Biron, read it over.</l>
                  <stage>Giving him the paper</stage>
                  <l>Where hadst thou it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaquenetta</speaker>
                  <l>Of Costard.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Where hadst thou it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>Of Dun Adramadio, Dun Adramadio.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Biron tears the letter</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>How now! what is in you? why dost thou tear it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>A toy, my liege, a toy: your grace needs not fear it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>It did move him to passion, and therefore let's hear
                     it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>It is Biron's writing, and here is his name.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Gathering up the pieces</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l><stage>To Costard</stage> Ah, you whoreson loggerhead! you
                     were</l>
                  <l>born to do me shame.</l>
                  <l>Guilty, my lord, guilty! I confess, I confess.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>That you three fools lack'd me fool to make up the
                     mess:</l>
                  <l>He, he, and you, and you, my liege, and I,</l>
                  <l>Are pick-purses in love, and we deserve to die.</l>

                  <l>O, dismiss this audience, and I shall tell you more.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Now the number is even.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>True, true; we are four.</l>
                  <l>Will these turtles be gone?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Hence, sirs; away!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Walk aside the true folk, and let the traitors stay.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Costard and Jaquenetta</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet lords, sweet lovers, O, let us embrace!</l>
                  <l>As true we are as flesh and blood can be:</l>
                  <l>The sea will ebb and flow, heaven show his face;</l>
                  <l>Young blood doth not obey an old decree:</l>
                  <l>We cannot cross the cause why we were born;</l>
                  <l>Therefore of all hands must we be forsworn.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What, did these rent lines show some love of thine?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Did they, quoth you? Who sees the heavenly Rosaline,</l>
                  <l>That, like a rude and savage man of Inde,</l>
                  <l>At the first opening of the gorgeous east,</l>

                  <l>Bows not his vassal head and strucken blind</l>
                  <l>Kisses the base ground with obedient breast?</l>
                  <l>What peremptory eagle-sighted eye</l>
                  <l>Dares look upon the heaven of her brow,</l>
                  <l>That is not blinded by her majesty?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What zeal, what fury hath inspired thee now?</l>

                  <l>My love, her mistress, is a gracious moon;</l>
                  <l>She an attending star, scarce seen a light.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>My eyes are then no eyes, nor I Biron:</l>
                  <l>O, but for my love, day would turn to night!</l>
                  <l>Of all complexions the cull'd sovereignty</l>
                  <l>Do meet, as at a fair, in her fair cheek,</l>

                  <l>Where several worthies make one dignity,</l>
                  <l>Where nothing wants that want itself doth seek.</l>
                  <l>Lend me the flourish of all gentle tongues,--</l>
                  <l>Fie, painted rhetoric! O, she needs it not:</l>
                  <l>To things of sale a seller's praise belongs,</l>
                  <l>She passes praise; then praise too short doth blot.</l>
                  <l>A wither'd hermit, five-score winters worn,</l>
                  <l>Might shake off fifty, looking in her eye:</l>
                  <l>Beauty doth varnish age, as if new-born,</l>

                  <l>And gives the crutch the cradle's infancy:</l>
                  <l>O, 'tis the sun that maketh all things shine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>By heaven, thy love is black as ebony.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Is ebony like her? O wood divine!</l>

                  <l>A wife of such wood were felicity.</l>
                  <l>O, who can give an oath? where is a book?</l>
                  <l>That I may swear beauty doth beauty lack,</l>
                  <l>If that she learn not of her eye to look:</l>
                  <l>No face is fair that is not full so black.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>O paradox! Black is the badge of hell,</l>

                  <l>The hue of dungeons and the suit of night;</l>
                  <l>And beauty's crest becomes the heavens well.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Devils soonest tempt, resembling spirits of light.</l>
                  <l>O, if in black my lady's brows be deck'd,</l>
                  <l>It mourns that painting and usurping hair</l>
                  <l>Should ravish doters with a false aspect;</l>

                  <l>And therefore is she born to make black fair.</l>
                  <l>Her favour turns the fashion of the days,</l>
                  <l>For native blood is counted painting now;</l>
                  <l>And therefore red, that would avoid dispraise,</l>
                  <l>Paints itself black, to imitate her brow.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>To look like her are chimney-sweepers black.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>And since her time are colliers counted bright.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>And Ethiopes of their sweet complexion crack.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Dark needs no candles now, for dark is light.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Your mistresses dare never come in rain,</l>
                  <l>For fear their colours should be wash'd away.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>'Twere good, yours did; for, sir, to tell you plain,</l>
                  <l>I'll find a fairer face not wash'd to-day.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I'll prove her fair, or talk till doomsday here.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>No devil will fright thee then so much as she.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>I never knew man hold vile stuff so dear.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Look, here's thy love: my foot and her face see.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>O, if the streets were paved with thine eyes,</l>
                  <l>Her feet were much too dainty for such tread!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>O, vile! then, as she goes, what upward lies</l>
                  <l>The street should see as she walk'd overhead.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>But what of this? are we not all in love?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing so sure; and thereby all forsworn.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>Then leave this chat; and, good Biron, now prove</l>
                  <l>Our loving lawful, and our faith not torn.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, marry, there; some flattery for this evil.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>O, some authority how to proceed;</l>

                  <l>Some tricks, some quillets, how to cheat the devil.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Some salve for perjury.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis more than need.</l>
                  <l>Have at you, then, affection's men at arms.</l>

                  <l>Consider what you first did swear unto,</l>
                  <l>To fast, to study, and to see no woman;</l>
                  <l>Flat treason 'gainst the kingly state of youth.</l>
                  <l>Say, can you fast? your stomachs are too young;</l>
                  <l>And abstinence engenders maladies.</l>
                  <l>And where that you have vow'd to study, lords,</l>
                  <l>In that each of you have forsworn his book,</l>
                  <l>Can you still dream and pore and thereon look?</l>
                  <l>For when would you, my lord, or you, or you,</l>

                  <l>Have found the ground of study's excellence</l>
                  <l>Without the beauty of a woman's face?</l>
                  <stage>From women's eyes this doctrine I derive; They are the
                     ground, the books, the academes From whence doth spring the
                     true Promethean fire</stage>
                  <l>Why, universal plodding poisons up</l>
                  <l>The nimble spirits in the arteries,</l>
                  <l>As motion and long-during action tires</l>
                  <l>The sinewy vigour of the traveller.</l>
                  <l>Now, for not looking on a woman's face,</l>
                  <l>You have in that forsworn the use of eyes</l>

                  <l>And study too, the causer of your vow;</l>
                  <l>For where is any author in the world</l>
                  <l>Teaches such beauty as a woman's eye?</l>
                  <l>Learning is but an adjunct to ourself</l>
                  <l>And where we are our learning likewise is:</l>
                  <l>Then when ourselves we see in ladies' eyes,</l>
                  <l>Do we not likewise see our learning there?</l>
                  <l>O, we have made a vow to study, lords,</l>
                  <l>And in that vow we have forsworn our books.</l>

                  <l>For when would you, my liege, or you, or you,</l>
                  <l>In leaden contemplation have found out</l>
                  <l>Such fiery numbers as the prompting eyes</l>
                  <l>Of beauty's tutors have enrich'd you with?</l>
                  <l>Other slow arts entirely keep the brain;</l>
                  <l>And therefore, finding barren practisers,</l>
                  <l>Scarce show a harvest of their heavy toil:</l>
                  <l>But love, first learned in a lady's eyes,</l>
                  <l>Lives not alone immured in the brain;</l>

                  <l>But, with the motion of all elements,</l>
                  <l>Courses as swift as thought in every power,</l>
                  <l>And gives to every power a double power,</l>
                  <l>Above their functions and their offices.</l>
                  <l>It adds a precious seeing to the eye;</l>
                  <l>A lover's eyes will gaze an eagle blind;</l>
                  <l>A lover's ear will hear the lowest sound,</l>
                  <l>When the suspicious head of theft is stopp'd:</l>
                  <l>Love's feeling is more soft and sensible</l>

                  <l>Than are the tender horns of cockl'd snails;</l>
                  <l>Love's tongue proves dainty Bacchus gross in taste:</l>
                  <l>For valour, is not Love a Hercules,</l>
                  <l>Still climbing trees in the Hesperides?</l>
                  <l>Subtle as Sphinx; as sweet and musical</l>
                  <l>As bright Apollo's lute, strung with his hair:</l>
                  <l>And when Love speaks, the voice of all the gods</l>
                  <l>Makes heaven drowsy with the harmony.</l>
                  <l>Never durst poet touch a pen to write</l>

                  <l>Until his ink were temper'd with Love's sighs;</l>
                  <l>O, then his lines would ravish savage ears</l>
                  <l>And plant in tyrants mild humility.</l>
                  <l>From women's eyes this doctrine I derive:</l>
                  <l>They sparkle still the right Promethean fire;</l>
                  <l>They are the books, the arts, the academes,</l>
                  <l>That show, contain and nourish all the world:</l>
                  <l>Else none at all in ought proves excellent.</l>
                  <l>Then fools you were these women to forswear,</l>

                  <l>Or keeping what is sworn, you will prove fools.</l>
                  <l>For wisdom's sake, a word that all men love,</l>
                  <l>Or for love's sake, a word that loves all men,</l>
                  <l>Or for men's sake, the authors of these women,</l>
                  <l>Or women's sake, by whom we men are men,</l>
                  <l>Let us once lose our oaths to find ourselves,</l>
                  <l>Or else we lose ourselves to keep our oaths.</l>
                  <l>It is religion to be thus forsworn,</l>
                  <l>For charity itself fulfills the law,</l>

                  <l>And who can sever love from charity?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Saint Cupid, then! and, soldiers, to the field!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Advance your standards, and upon them, lords;</l>
                  <l>Pell-mell, down with them! but be first advised,</l>

                  <l>In conflict that you get the sun of them.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Now to plain-dealing; lay these glozes by:</l>
                  <l>Shall we resolve to woo these girls of France?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>And win them too: therefore let us devise</l>

                  <l>Some entertainment for them in their tents.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>First, from the park let us conduct them thither;</l>
                  <l>Then homeward every man attach the hand</l>
                  <l>Of his fair mistress: in the afternoon</l>
                  <l>We will with some strange pastime solace them,</l>
                  <l>Such as the shortness of the time can shape;</l>

                  <l>For revels, dances, masks and merry hours</l>
                  <l>Forerun fair Love, strewing her way with flowers.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Away, away! no time shall be omitted</l>
                  <l>That will betime, and may by us be fitted.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Allons! allons! Sow'd cockle reap'd no corn;</l>
                  <l>And justice always whirls in equal measure:</l>
                  <l>Light wenches may prove plagues to men forsworn;</l>
                  <l>If so, our copper buys no better treasure.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>

         </div>

         <div type="act" n="5">
            <div type="scene" n="1">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter Holofernes, Sir Nathaniel, and Dull</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Satis quod sufficit.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>

                  <l>I praise God for you, sir: your reasons at dinner</l>
                  <l>have been sharp and sententious; pleasant without</l>
                  <l>scurrility, witty without affection, audacious without</l>
                  <l>impudency, learned without opinion, and strange with-</l>
                  <l>out heresy. I did converse this quondam day with</l>
                  <l>a companion of the king's, who is intituled, nomi-</l>
                  <l>nated, or called, Don Adriano.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Novi hominem tanquam te: his humour is lofty, his</l>
                  <l>discourse peremptory, his tongue filed, his eye</l>
                  <l>ambitious, his gait majestical, and his general</l>
                  <l>behavior vain, ridiculous, and thrasonical. He is</l>
                  <l>too picked, too spruce, too affected, too odd, as it</l>
                  <l>were, too peregrinate, as I may call it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>A most singular and choice epithet.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Draws out his table-book</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>He draweth out the thread of his verbosity finer</l>
                  <l>than the staple of his argument. I abhor such</l>

                  <l>fanatical phantasimes, such insociable and</l>
                  <l>point-devise companions; such rackers of</l>
                  <l>orthography, as to speak dout, fine, when he should</l>
                  <l>say doubt; det, when he should pronounce debt,--d,</l>
                  <l>e, b, t, not d, e, t: he clepeth a calf, cauf;</l>
                  <l>half, hauf; neighbour vocatur nebor; neigh</l>
                  <l>abbreviated ne. This is abhominable,--which he</l>
                  <l>would call abbominable: it insinuateth me of</l>
                  <l>insanie: anne intelligis, domine? to make frantic,
                     lunatic.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Laus Deo, bene intelligo.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Bon, bon, fort bon, Priscian! a little scratch'd,</l>
                  <l>'twill serve.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Videsne quis venit?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Video, et gaudeo.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Don Adriano, Moth, and Costard</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Chirrah!</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>To Moth</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Quare chirrah, not sirrah?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Men of peace, well encountered.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Most military sir, salutation.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside to Costard</stage> They have been at a great
                     feast</l>
                  <l>of languages, and stolen the scraps.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>O, they have lived long on the alms-basket of words.</l>
                  <l>I marvel thy master hath not eaten thee for a word;</l>

                  <l>for thou art not so long by the head as</l>
                  <l>honorificabilitudinitatibus: thou art easier</l>
                  <l>swallowed than a flap-dragon.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Peace! the peal begins.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>

                  <l><stage>To Holofernes</stage> Monsieur, are you not
                     lettered?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes; he teaches boys the hornbook. What is a,</l>
                  <l>b, spelt backward, with the horn on his head?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>

                  <l>Ba, pueritia, with a horn added.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Ba, most silly sheep with a horn. You hear his
                     learning.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Quis, quis, thou consonant?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>The third of the five vowels, if you repeat them; or</l>
                  <l>the fifth, if I.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>I will repeat them,--a, e, i,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>The sheep: the other two concludes it,--o, u.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Now, by the salt wave of the Mediterraneum, a sweet</l>
                  <l>touch, a quick venue of wit! snip, snap, quick and</l>
                  <l>home! it rejoiceth my intellect: true wit!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Offered by a child to an old man; which is wit-old.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>What is the figure? what is the figure?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>

                  <l>Horns.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Thou disputest like an infant: go, whip thy gig.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Lend me your horn to make one, and I will whip about</l>
                  <l>your infamy circum circa,--a gig of a cuckold's horn.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>An I had but one penny in the world, thou shouldst</l>
                  <l>have it to buy gingerbread: hold, there is the very</l>
                  <l>remuneration I had of thy master, thou halfpenny</l>
                  <l>purse of wit, thou pigeon-egg of discretion. O, an</l>
                  <l>the heavens were so pleased that thou wert but my</l>
                  <l>bastard, what a joyful father wouldst thou make me!</l>

                  <l>Go to; thou hast it ad dunghill, at the fingers'</l>
                  <l>ends, as they say.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>O, I smell false Latin; dunghill for unguem.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Arts-man, preambulate, we will be singled from the</l>

                  <l>barbarous. Do you not educate youth at the</l>
                  <l>charge-house on the top of the mountain?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Or mons, the hill.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>At your sweet pleasure, for the mountain.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>I do, sans question.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, it is the king's most sweet pleasure and</l>
                  <l>affection to congratulate the Princess at her</l>
                  <l>pavilion in the posteriors of this day, which the</l>

                  <l>rude multitude call the afternoon.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>The posterior of the day, most generous sir, is</l>
                  <l>liable, congruent and measurable for the afternoon:</l>
                  <l>the word is well culled, chose, sweet and apt, I do</l>
                  <l>assure you, sir, I do assure.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the king is a noble gentleman, and my familiar,</l>
                  <l>I do assure ye, very good friend: for what is</l>
                  <l>inward between us, let it pass. I do beseech thee,</l>
                  <l>remember thy courtesy; I beseech thee, apparel thy</l>
                  <l>head: and among other important and most serious</l>
                  <l>designs, and of great import indeed, too, but let</l>
                  <l>that pass: for I must tell thee, it will please his</l>

                  <l>grace, by the world, sometime to lean upon my poor</l>
                  <l>shoulder, and with his royal finger, thus, dally</l>
                  <l>with my excrement, with my mustachio; but, sweet</l>
                  <l>heart, let that pass. By the world, I recount no</l>
                  <l>fable: some certain special honours it pleaseth his</l>
                  <l>greatness to impart to Armado, a soldier, a man of</l>
                  <l>travel, that hath seen the world; but let that pass.</l>
                  <l>The very all of all is,--but, sweet heart, I do</l>
                  <l>implore secrecy,--that the king would have me</l>

                  <l>present the Princess, sweet chuck, with some</l>
                  <l>delightful ostentation, or show, or pageant, or</l>
                  <l>antique, or firework. Now, understanding that the</l>
                  <l>curate and your sweet self are good at such</l>
                  <l>eruptions and sudden breaking out of mirth, as it</l>
                  <l>were, I have acquainted you withal, to the end to</l>
                  <l>crave your assistance.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you shall present before her the Nine Worthies.</l>
                  <l>Sir, as concerning some entertainment of time, some</l>
                  <l>show in the posterior of this day, to be rendered by</l>
                  <l>our assistants, at the king's command, and this most</l>
                  <l>gallant, illustrate, and learned gentleman, before</l>
                  <l>the Princess; I say none so fit as to present the</l>
                  <l>Nine Worthies.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>Where will you find men worthy enough to present them?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Joshua, yourself; myself and this gallant gentleman,</l>
                  <l>Judas Maccabaeus; this swain, because of his great</l>
                  <l>limb or joint, shall pass Pompey the Great; the</l>

                  <l>page, Hercules,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon, sir; error: he is not quantity enough for</l>
                  <l>that Worthy's thumb: he is not so big as the end of his
                     club.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I have audience? he shall present Hercules in</l>

                  <l>minority: his enter and exit shall be strangling a</l>
                  <l>snake; and I will have an apology for that purpose.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>An excellent device! so, if any of the audience</l>
                  <l>hiss, you may cry 'Well done, Hercules! now thou</l>
                  <l>crushest the snake!' that is the way to make an</l>
                  <l>offence gracious, though few have the grace to do it.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>For the rest of the Worthies?--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>I will play three myself.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Thrice-worthy gentleman!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I tell you a thing?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>We attend.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>We will have, if this fadge not, an antique. I</l>
                  <l>beseech you, follow.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Via, goodman Dull! thou hast spoken no word all this
                     while.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>
                  <l>Nor understood none neither, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Allons! we will employ thee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dull</speaker>

                  <l>I'll make one in a dance, or so; or I will play</l>
                  <l>On the tabour to the Worthies, and let them dance the
                     hay.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Most Dull, honest Dull! To our sport, away!</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>

            <div type="scene" n="2">
               <head>The same.</head>
               <stage>Enter the Princess, Katherine, Rosaline, and Maria</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet hearts, we shall be rich ere we depart,</l>
                  <l>If fairings come thus plentifully in:</l>
                  <l>A lady wall'd about with diamonds!</l>
                  <l>Look you what I have from the loving king.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Madame, came nothing else along with that?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but this! yes, as much love in rhyme</l>
                  <l>As would be cramm'd up in a sheet of paper,</l>
                  <l>Writ o' both sides the leaf, margent and all,</l>

                  <l>That he was fain to seal on Cupid's name.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>That was the way to make his godhead wax,</l>
                  <l>For he hath been five thousand years a boy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, and a shrewd unhappy gallows too.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>You'll ne'er be friends with him; a' kill'd your
                     sister.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>He made her melancholy, sad, and heavy;</l>
                  <l>And so she died: had she been light, like you,</l>
                  <l>Of such a merry, nimble, stirring spirit,</l>

                  <l>She might ha' been a grandam ere she died:</l>
                  <l>And so may you; for a light heart lives long.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>What's your dark meaning, mouse, of this light word?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>A light condition in a beauty dark.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>We need more light to find your meaning out.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>You'll mar the light by taking it in snuff;</l>
                  <l>Therefore I'll darkly end the argument.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Look what you do, you do it still i' the dark.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>So do not you, for you are a light wench.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>

                  <l>Indeed I weigh not you, and therefore light.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>You weigh me not? O, that's you care not for me.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Great reason; for 'past cure is still past care.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Well bandied both; a set of wit well play'd.</l>
                  <l>But Rosaline, you have a favour too:</l>
                  <l>Who sent it? and what is it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>I would you knew:</l>

                  <l>An if my face were but as fair as yours,</l>
                  <l>My favour were as great; be witness this.</l>
                  <l>Nay, I have verses too, I thank Biron:</l>
                  <l>The numbers true; and, were the numbering too,</l>
                  <l>I were the fairest goddess on the ground:</l>
                  <l>I am compared to twenty thousand fairs.</l>
                  <l>O, he hath drawn my picture in his letter!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Any thing like?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Much in the letters; nothing in the praise.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Beauteous as ink; a good conclusion.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Fair as a text B in a copy-book.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>'Ware pencils, ho! let me not die your debtor,</l>
                  <l>My red dominical, my golden letter:</l>
                  <l>O, that your face were not so full of O's!</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>A pox of that jest! and I beshrew all shrows.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>But, Katherine, what was sent to you from fair Dumain?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, this glove.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Did he not send you twain?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, madam, and moreover</l>

                  <l>Some thousand verses of a faithful lover,</l>
                  <l>A huge translation of hypocrisy,</l>
                  <l>Vilely compiled, profound simplicity.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>This and these pearls to me sent Longaville:</l>
                  <l>The letter is too long by half a mile.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>I think no less. Dost thou not wish in heart</l>
                  <l>The chain were longer and the letter short?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, or I would these hands might never part.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>We are wise girls to mock our lovers so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>They are worse fools to purchase mocking so.</l>
                  <l>That same Biron I'll torture ere I go:</l>
                  <l>O that I knew he were but in by the week!</l>
                  <l>How I would make him fawn and beg and seek</l>

                  <l>And wait the season and observe the times</l>
                  <l>And spend his prodigal wits in bootless rhymes</l>
                  <l>And shape his service wholly to my hests</l>
                  <l>And make him proud to make me proud that jests!</l>
                  <l>So perttaunt-like would I o'ersway his state</l>
                  <l>That he should be my fool and I his fate.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>None are so surely caught, when they are catch'd,</l>
                  <l>As wit turn'd fool: folly, in wisdom hatch'd,</l>
                  <l>Hath wisdom's warrant and the help of school</l>
                  <l>And wit's own grace to grace a learned fool.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>The blood of youth burns not with such excess</l>
                  <l>As gravity's revolt to wantonness.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Folly in fools bears not so strong a note</l>
                  <l>As foolery in the wise, when wit doth dote;</l>
                  <l>Since all the power thereof it doth apply</l>
                  <l>To prove, by wit, worth in simplicity.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Here comes Boyet, and mirth is in his face.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Boyet</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>O, I am stabb'd with laughter! Where's her grace?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Thy news Boyet?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Prepare, madam, prepare!</l>
                  <l>Arm, wenches, arm! encounters mounted are</l>
                  <l>Against your peace: Love doth approach disguised,</l>
                  <l>Armed in arguments; you'll be surprised:</l>
                  <l>Muster your wits; stand in your own defence;</l>

                  <l>Or hide your heads like cowards, and fly hence.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Saint Denis to Saint Cupid! What are they</l>
                  <l>That charge their breath against us? say, scout, say.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Under the cool shade of a sycamore</l>

                  <l>I thought to close mine eyes some half an hour;</l>
                  <l>When, lo! to interrupt my purposed rest,</l>
                  <l>Toward that shade I might behold addrest</l>
                  <l>The king and his companions: warily</l>
                  <l>I stole into a neighbour thicket by,</l>
                  <l>And overheard what you shall overhear,</l>
                  <l>That, by and by, disguised they will be here.</l>
                  <l>Their herald is a pretty knavish page,</l>
                  <l>That well by heart hath conn'd his embassage:</l>

                  <l>Action and accent did they teach him there;</l>
                  <l>'Thus must thou speak,' and 'thus thy body bear:'</l>
                  <l>And ever and anon they made a doubt</l>
                  <l>Presence majestical would put him out,</l>
                  <l>'For,' quoth the king, 'an angel shalt thou see;</l>
                  <l>Yet fear not thou, but speak audaciously.'</l>
                  <l>The boy replied, 'An angel is not evil;</l>
                  <l>I should have fear'd her had she been a devil.'</l>
                  <l>With that, all laugh'd and clapp'd him on the shoulder,</l>

                  <l>Making the bold wag by their praises bolder:</l>
                  <l>One rubb'd his elbow thus, and fleer'd and swore</l>
                  <l>A better speech was never spoke before;</l>
                  <l>Another, with his finger and his thumb,</l>
                  <l>Cried, 'Via! we will do't, come what will come;'</l>
                  <l>The third he caper'd, and cried, 'All goes well;'</l>
                  <l>The fourth turn'd on the toe, and down he fell.</l>
                  <l>With that, they all did tumble on the ground,</l>
                  <l>With such a zealous laughter, so profound,</l>

                  <l>That in this spleen ridiculous appears,</l>
                  <l>To cheque their folly, passion's solemn tears.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>But what, but what, come they to visit us?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>They do, they do: and are apparell'd thus.</l>

                  <l>Like Muscovites or Russians, as I guess.</l>
                  <l>Their purpose is to parle, to court and dance;</l>
                  <l>And every one his love-feat will advance</l>
                  <l>Unto his several mistress, which they'll know</l>
                  <l>By favours several which they did bestow.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>And will they so? the gallants shall be task'd;</l>

                  <l>For, ladies, we shall every one be mask'd;</l>
                  <l>And not a man of them shall have the grace,</l>
                  <l>Despite of suit, to see a lady's face.</l>
                  <l>Hold, Rosaline, this favour thou shalt wear,</l>
                  <l>And then the king will court thee for his dear;</l>
                  <l>Hold, take thou this, my sweet, and give me thine,</l>
                  <l>So shall Biron take me for Rosaline.</l>
                  <l>And change your favours too; so shall your loves</l>
                  <l>Woo contrary, deceived by these removes.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Come on, then; wear the favours most in sight.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>But in this changing what is your intent?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>The effect of my intent is to cross theirs:</l>
                  <l>They do it but in mocking merriment;</l>
                  <l>And mock for mock is only my intent.</l>
                  <l>Their several counsels they unbosom shall</l>
                  <l>To loves mistook, and so be mock'd withal</l>
                  <l>Upon the next occasion that we meet,</l>
                  <l>With visages displayed, to talk and greet.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>But shall we dance, if they desire to't?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>No, to the death, we will not move a foot;</l>
                  <l>Nor to their penn'd speech render we no grace,</l>
                  <l>But while 'tis spoke each turn away her face.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Why, that contempt will kill the speaker's heart,</l>
                  <l>And quite divorce his memory from his part.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore I do it; and I make no doubt</l>
                  <l>The rest will ne'er come in, if he be out</l>

                  <l>There's no such sport as sport by sport o'erthrown,</l>
                  <l>To make theirs ours and ours none but our own:</l>
                  <l>So shall we stay, mocking intended game,</l>
                  <l>And they, well mock'd, depart away with shame.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Trumpets sound within</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>The trumpet sounds: be mask'd; the maskers come.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>The Ladies mask</stage>
               <stage>Enter Blackamoors with music; Moth; Ferdinand, Biron,
                  Longaville, and Dumain, in Russian habits, and masked</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>All hail, the richest beauties on the earth!--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Beauties no richer than rich taffeta.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>A holy parcel of the fairest dames.</l>
                  <stage>The Ladies turn their backs to him</stage>
                  <l>That ever turn'd their--backs--to mortal views!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside to Moth</stage> Their eyes, villain, their
                     eyes!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>That ever turn'd their eyes to mortal views!--Out--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>True; out indeed.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Out of your favours, heavenly spirits, vouchsafe</l>
                  <l>Not to behold--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l><stage>Aside to Moth</stage> Once to behold, rogue.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Once to behold with your sun-beamed eyes,</l>
                  <l>--with your sun-beamed eyes--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>They will not answer to that epithet;</l>
                  <l>You were best call it 'daughter-beamed eyes.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>They do not mark me, and that brings me out.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Is this your perfectness? be gone, you rogue!</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Exit Moth</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>What would these strangers? know their minds, Boyet:</l>
                  <l>If they do speak our language, 'tis our will:</l>
                  <l>That some plain man recount their purposes</l>
                  <l>Know what they would.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>What would you with the Princess?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but peace and gentle visitation.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>What would they, say they?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but peace and gentle visitation.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Why, that they have; and bid them so be gone.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>She says, you have it, and you may be gone.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Say to her, we have measured many miles</l>
                  <l>To tread a measure with her on this grass.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>They say, that they have measured many a mile</l>
                  <l>To tread a measure with you on this grass.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>It is not so. Ask them how many inches</l>
                  <l>Is in one mile: if they have measured many,</l>

                  <l>The measure then of one is easily told.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>If to come hither you have measured miles,</l>
                  <l>And many miles, the Princess bids you tell</l>
                  <l>How many inches doth fill up one mile.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Tell her, we measure them by weary steps.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>She hears herself.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>How many weary steps,</l>
                  <l>Of many weary miles you have o'ergone,</l>

                  <l>Are number'd in the travel of one mile?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>We number nothing that we spend for you:</l>
                  <l>Our duty is so rich, so infinite,</l>
                  <l>That we may do it still without accompt.</l>
                  <l>Vouchsafe to show the sunshine of your face,</l>
                  <l>That we, like savages, may worship it.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>My face is but a moon, and clouded too.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Blessed are clouds, to do as such clouds do!</l>
                  <l>Vouchsafe, bright moon, and these thy stars, to shine,</l>
                  <l>Those clouds removed, upon our watery eyne.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>O vain petitioner! beg a greater matter;</l>
                  <l>Thou now request'st but moonshine in the water.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Then, in our measure do but vouchsafe one change.</l>
                  <l>Thou bid'st me beg: this begging is not strange.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Play, music, then! Nay, you must do it soon.</l>
                  <stage>Music plays</stage>
                  <l>Not yet! no dance! Thus change I like the moon.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Will you not dance? How come you thus estranged?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>You took the moon at full, but now she's changed.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Yet still she is the moon, and I the man.</l>
                  <l>The music plays; vouchsafe some motion to it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Our ears vouchsafe it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>But your legs should do it.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>

                  <l>Since you are strangers and come here by chance,</l>
                  <l>We'll not be nice: take hands. We will not dance.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Why take we hands, then?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Only to part friends:</l>

                  <l>Curtsy, sweet hearts; and so the measure ends.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>More measure of this measure; be not nice.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>We can afford no more at such a price.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Prize you yourselves: what buys your company?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Your absence only.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>That can never be.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Then cannot we be bought: and so, adieu;</l>
                  <l>Twice to your visor, and half once to you.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>If you deny to dance, let's hold more chat.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>In private, then.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>I am best pleased with that.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>They converse apart</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>White-handed mistress, one sweet word with thee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Honey, and milk, and sugar; there is three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then, two treys, and if you grow so nice,</l>
                  <l>Metheglin, wort, and malmsey: well run, dice!</l>
                  <l>There's half-a-dozen sweets.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Seventh sweet, adieu:</l>
                  <l>Since you can cog, I'll play no more with you.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>One word in secret.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Let it not be sweet.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Thou grievest my gall.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Gall! bitter.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore meet.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>They converse apart</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Will you vouchsafe with me to change a word?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Name it.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Fair lady,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Say you so? Fair lord,--</l>
                  <l>Take that for your fair lady.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Please it you,</l>
                  <l>As much in private, and I'll bid adieu.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>They converse apart</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>

                  <l>What, was your vizard made without a tongue?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>I know the reason, lady, why you ask.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>O for your reason! quickly, sir; I long.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>You have a double tongue within your mask,</l>
                  <l>And would afford my speechless vizard half.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Veal, quoth the Dutchman. Is not 'veal' a calf?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>A calf, fair lady!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>No, a fair lord calf.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>

                  <l>Let's part the word.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>No, I'll not be your half</l>
                  <l>Take all, and wean it; it may prove an ox.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Look, how you butt yourself in these sharp mocks!</l>

                  <l>Will you give horns, chaste lady? do not so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Then die a calf, before your horns do grow.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>One word in private with you, ere I die.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Bleat softly then; the butcher hears you cry.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>They converse apart</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>The tongues of mocking wenches are as keen</l>

                  <l>As is the razor's edge invisible,</l>
                  <l>Cutting a smaller hair than may be seen,</l>
                  <l>Above the sense of sense; so sensible</l>
                  <l>Seemeth their conference; their conceits have wings</l>
                  <l>Fleeter than arrows, bullets, wind, thought, swifter
                     things.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Not one word more, my maids; break off, break off.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>By heaven, all dry-beaten with pure scoff!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell, mad wenches; you have simple wits.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Twenty adieus, my frozen Muscovits.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt Ferdinand, Lords, and Blackamoors</stage>
                  <l>Are these the breed of wits so wonder'd at?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Tapers they are, with your sweet breaths puff'd out.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Well-liking wits they have; gross, gross; fat, fat.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>O poverty in wit, kingly-poor flout!</l>
                  <l>Will they not, think you, hang themselves tonight?</l>
                  <l>Or ever, but in vizards, show their faces?</l>
                  <l>This pert Biron was out of countenance quite.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>O, they were all in lamentable cases!</l>
                  <l>The king was weeping-ripe for a good word.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Biron did swear himself out of all suit.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Dumain was at my service, and his sword:</l>
                  <l>No point, quoth I; my servant straight was mute.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Lord Longaville said, I came o'er his heart;</l>
                  <l>And trow you what he called me?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Qualm, perhaps.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, in good faith.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Go, sickness as thou art!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Well, better wits have worn plain statute-caps.</l>
                  <l>But will you hear? the king is my love sworn.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>And quick Biron hath plighted faith to me.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>And Longaville was for my service born.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>Dumain is mine, as sure as bark on tree.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, and pretty mistresses, give ear:</l>
                  <l>Immediately they will again be here</l>
                  <l>In their own shapes; for it can never be</l>
                  <l>They will digest this harsh indignity.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Will they return?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>They will, they will, God knows,</l>
                  <l>And leap for joy, though they are lame with blows:</l>
                  <l>Therefore change favours; and, when they repair,</l>
                  <l>Blow like sweet roses in this summer air.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>How blow? how blow? speak to be understood.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Fair ladies mask'd are roses in their bud;</l>
                  <l>Dismask'd, their damask sweet commixture shown,</l>
                  <l>Are angels vailing clouds, or roses blown.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Avaunt, perplexity! What shall we do,</l>
                  <l>If they return in their own shapes to woo?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Good madam, if by me you'll be advised,</l>
                  <l>Let's, mock them still, as well known as disguised:</l>

                  <l>Let us complain to them what fools were here,</l>
                  <l>Disguised like Muscovites, in shapeless gear;</l>
                  <l>And wonder what they were and to what end</l>
                  <l>Their shallow shows and prologue vilely penn'd</l>
                  <l>And their rough carriage so ridiculous,</l>
                  <l>Should be presented at our tent to us.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>Ladies, withdraw: the gallants are at hand.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Whip to our tents, as roes run o'er land.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Exeunt Princess, Rosaline, Katherine, and Maria</stage>
               <stage>Re-enter Ferdinand, Biron, Longaville, and Dumain, in
                  their proper habits</stage>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Fair sir, God save you! Where's the Princess?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Gone to her tent. Please it your majesty</l>
                  <l>Command me any service to her thither?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>That she vouchsafe me audience for one word.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>I will; and so will she, I know, my lord.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>This fellow pecks up wit as pigeons pease,</l>
                  <l>And utters it again when God doth please:</l>
                  <l>He is wit's pedler, and retails his wares</l>
                  <l>At wakes and wassails, meetings, markets, fairs;</l>
                  <l>And we that sell by gross, the Lord doth know,</l>
                  <l>Have not the grace to grace it with such show.</l>
                  <l>This gallant pins the wenches on his sleeve;</l>
                  <l>Had he been Adam, he had tempted Eve;</l>
                  <l>A' can carve too, and lisp: why, this is he</l>

                  <l>That kiss'd his hand away in courtesy;</l>
                  <l>This is the ape of form, monsieur the nice,</l>
                  <l>That, when he plays at tables, chides the dice</l>
                  <l>In honourable terms: nay, he can sing</l>
                  <l>A mean most meanly; and in ushering</l>
                  <l>Mend him who can: the ladies call him sweet;</l>
                  <l>The stairs, as he treads on them, kiss his feet:</l>
                  <l>This is the flower that smiles on every one,</l>
                  <l>To show his teeth as white as whale's bone;</l>

                  <l>And consciences, that will not die in debt,</l>
                  <l>Pay him the due of honey-tongued Boyet.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>A blister on his sweet tongue, with my heart,</l>
                  <l>That put Armado's page out of his part!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>See where it comes! Behavior, what wert thou</l>
                  <l>Till this madman show'd thee? and what art thou now?</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Re-enter the Princess, ushered by Boyet, Rosaline, Maria,
                  and Katherine</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>All hail, sweet madam, and fair time of day!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>'Fair' in 'all hail' is foul, as I conceive.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Construe my speeches better, if you may.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Then wish me better; I will give you leave.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>We came to visit you, and purpose now</l>
                  <l>To lead you to our court; vouchsafe it then.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>This field shall hold me; and so hold your vow:</l>

                  <l>Nor God, nor I, delights in perjured men.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Rebuke me not for that which you provoke:</l>
                  <l>The virtue of your eye must break my oath.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>You nickname virtue; vice you should have spoke;</l>

                  <l>For virtue's office never breaks men's troth.</l>
                  <l>Now by my maiden honour, yet as pure</l>
                  <l>As the unsullied lily, I protest,</l>
                  <l>A world of torments though I should endure,</l>
                  <l>I would not yield to be your house's guest;</l>
                  <l>So much I hate a breaking cause to be</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly oaths, vow'd with integrity.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>O, you have lived in desolation here,</l>
                  <l>Unseen, unvisited, much to our shame.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Not so, my lord; it is not so, I swear;</l>
                  <l>We have had pastimes here and pleasant game:</l>
                  <l>A mess of Russians left us but of late.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>How, madam! Russians!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, in truth, my lord;</l>
                  <l>Trim gallants, full of courtship and of state.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, speak true. It is not so, my lord:</l>
                  <l>My lady, to the manner of the days,</l>
                  <l>In courtesy gives undeserving praise.</l>
                  <l>We four indeed confronted were with four</l>
                  <l>In Russian habit: here they stay'd an hour,</l>
                  <l>And talk'd apace; and in that hour, my lord,</l>
                  <l>They did not bless us with one happy word.</l>

                  <l>I dare not call them fools; but this I think,</l>
                  <l>When they are thirsty, fools would fain have drink.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>This jest is dry to me. Fair gentle sweet,</l>
                  <l>Your wit makes wise things foolish: when we greet,</l>
                  <l>With eyes best seeing, heaven's fiery eye,</l>
                  <l>By light we lose light: your capacity</l>

                  <l>Is of that nature that to your huge store</l>
                  <l>Wise things seem foolish and rich things but poor.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>This proves you wise and rich, for in my eye,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I am a fool, and full of poverty.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>But that you take what doth to you belong,</l>
                  <l>It were a fault to snatch words from my tongue.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>O, I am yours, and all that I possess!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>All the fool mine?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot give you less.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>

                  <l>Which of the vizards was it that you wore?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Where? when? what vizard? why demand you this?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>There, then, that vizard; that superfluous case</l>
                  <l>That hid the worse and show'd the better face.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>We are descried; they'll mock us now downright.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Let us confess and turn it to a jest.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Amazed, my lord? why looks your highness sad?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Help, hold his brows! he'll swoon! Why look you pale?</l>
                  <l>Sea-sick, I think, coming from Muscovy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Thus pour the stars down plagues for perjury.</l>
                  <l>Can any face of brass hold longer out?</l>
                  <l>Here stand I lady, dart thy skill at me;</l>
                  <l>Bruise me with scorn, confound me with a flout;</l>
                  <l>Thrust thy sharp wit quite through my ignorance;</l>
                  <l>Cut me to pieces with thy keen conceit;</l>
                  <l>And I will wish thee never more to dance,</l>
                  <l>Nor never more in Russian habit wait.</l>
                  <l>O, never will I trust to speeches penn'd,</l>

                  <l>Nor to the motion of a schoolboy's tongue,</l>
                  <l>Nor never come in vizard to my friend,</l>
                  <l>Nor woo in rhyme, like a blind harper's song!</l>
                  <l>Taffeta phrases, silken terms precise,</l>
                  <l>Three-piled hyperboles, spruce affectation,</l>
                  <l>Figures pedantical; these summer-flies</l>
                  <l>Have blown me full of maggot ostentation:</l>
                  <l>I do forswear them; and I here protest,</l>
                  <l>By this white glove;--how white the hand, God knows!--</l>

                  <l>Henceforth my wooing mind shall be express'd</l>
                  <l>In russet yeas and honest kersey noes:</l>
                  <l>And, to begin, wench,--so God help me, la!--</l>
                  <l>My love to thee is sound, sans crack or flaw.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Sans sans, I pray you.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Yet I have a trick</l>
                  <l>Of the old rage: bear with me, I am sick;</l>
                  <l>I'll leave it by degrees. Soft, let us see:</l>
                  <l>Write, 'Lord have mercy on us' on those three;</l>
                  <l>They are infected; in their hearts it lies;</l>
                  <l>They have the plague, and caught it of your eyes;</l>
                  <l>These lords are visited; you are not free,</l>

                  <l>For the Lord's tokens on you do I see.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>No, they are free that gave these tokens to us.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Our states are forfeit: seek not to undo us.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>It is not so; for how can this be true,</l>
                  <l>That you stand forfeit, being those that sue?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Peace! for I will not have to do with you.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Nor shall not, if I do as I intend.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Speak for yourselves; my wit is at an end.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>Teach us, sweet madam, for our rude transgression</l>
                  <l>Some fair excuse.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>The fairest is confession.</l>
                  <l>Were not you here but even now disguised?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>Madam, I was.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>And were you well advised?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>I was, fair madam.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>When you then were here,</l>
                  <l>What did you whisper in your lady's ear?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>That more than all the world I did respect her.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>When she shall challenge this, you will reject her.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Upon mine honour, no.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Peace, peace! forbear:</l>
                  <l>Your oath once broke, you force not to forswear.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Despise me, when I break this oath of mine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>I will: and therefore keep it. Rosaline,</l>

                  <l>What did the Russian whisper in your ear?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, he swore that he did hold me dear</l>
                  <l>As precious eyesight, and did value me</l>
                  <l>Above this world; adding thereto moreover</l>
                  <l>That he would wed me, or else die my lover.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>God give thee joy of him! the noble lord</l>
                  <l>Most honourably doth unhold his word.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>What mean you, madam? by my life, my troth,</l>
                  <l>I never swore this lady such an oath.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>By heaven, you did; and to confirm it plain,</l>
                  <l>You gave me this: but take it, sir, again.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>My faith and this the Princess I did give:</l>
                  <l>I knew her by this jewel on her sleeve.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon me, sir, this jewel did she wear;</l>
                  <l>And Lord Biron, I thank him, is my dear.</l>
                  <l>What, will you have me, or your pearl again?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Neither of either; I remit both twain.</l>

                  <l>I see the trick on't: here was a consent,</l>
                  <l>Knowing aforehand of our merriment,</l>
                  <l>To dash it like a Christmas comedy:</l>
                  <l>Some carry-tale, some please-man, some slight zany,</l>
                  <l>Some mumble-news, some trencher-knight, some Dick,</l>
                  <l>That smiles his cheek in years and knows the trick</l>
                  <l>To make my lady laugh when she's disposed,</l>
                  <l>Told our intents before; which once disclosed,</l>
                  <l>The ladies did change favours: and then we,</l>

                  <l>Following the signs, woo'd but the sign of she.</l>
                  <l>Now, to our perjury to add more terror,</l>
                  <l>We are again forsworn, in will and error.</l>
                  <l>Much upon this it is: and might not you</l>
                  <stage>To Boyet</stage>
                  <l>Forestall our sport, to make us thus untrue?</l>
                  <l>Do not you know my lady's foot by the squier,</l>
                  <l>And laugh upon the apple of her eye?</l>
                  <l>And stand between her back, sir, and the fire,</l>

                  <l>Holding a trencher, jesting merrily?</l>
                  <l>You put our page out: go, you are allow'd;</l>
                  <l>Die when you will, a smock shall be your shroud.</l>
                  <l>You leer upon me, do you? there's an eye</l>
                  <l>Wounds like a leaden sword.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Full merrily</l>

                  <l>Hath this brave manage, this career, been run.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Lo, he is tilting straight! Peace! I have done.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Costard</stage>
                  <l>Welcome, pure wit! thou partest a fair fray.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>O Lord, sir, they would know</l>
                  <l>Whether the three Worthies shall come in or no.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>What, are there but three?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>No, sir; but it is vara fine,</l>

                  <l>For every one pursents three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>And three times thrice is nine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Not so, sir; under correction, sir; I hope it is not
                     so.</l>
                  <l>You cannot beg us, sir, I can assure you, sir we know</l>

                  <l>what we know:</l>
                  <l>I hope, sir, three times thrice, sir,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Is not nine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Under correction, sir, we know whereuntil it doth
                     amount.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>By Jove, I always took three threes for nine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>O Lord, sir, it were pity you should get your living</l>
                  <l>by reckoning, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>How much is it?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>O Lord, sir, the parties themselves, the actors,</l>
                  <l>sir, will show whereuntil it doth amount: for mine</l>
                  <l>own part, I am, as they say, but to parfect one man</l>

                  <l>in one poor man, Pompion the Great, sir.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou one of the Worthies?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>It pleased them to think me worthy of Pompion the</l>
                  <l>Great: for mine own part, I know not the degree of</l>

                  <l>the Worthy, but I am to stand for him.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Go, bid them prepare.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>We will turn it finely off, sir; we will take</l>
                  <l>some care.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Biron, they will shame us: let them not approach.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>We are shame-proof, my lord: and tis some policy</l>

                  <l>To have one show worse than the king's and his company.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>I say they shall not come.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, my good lord, let me o'errule you now:</l>
                  <l>That sport best pleases that doth least know how:</l>

                  <l>Where zeal strives to content, and the contents</l>
                  <l>Dies in the zeal of that which it presents:</l>
                  <l>Their form confounded makes most form in mirth,</l>
                  <l>When great things labouring perish in their birth.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>A right description of our sport, my lord.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Enter Don Adriano</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Anointed, I implore so much expense of thy royal</l>
                  <l>sweet breath as will utter a brace of words.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Converses apart with Ferdinand, and delivers him a
                  paper</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Doth this man serve God?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Why ask you?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>He speaks not like a man of God's making.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>That is all one, my fair, sweet, honey monarch; for,</l>
                  <l>I protest, the schoolmaster is exceeding</l>
                  <l>fantastical; too, too vain, too too vain: but we</l>
                  <l>will put it, as they say, to fortuna de la guerra.</l>
                  <l>I wish you the peace of mind, most royal couplement!</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Exit</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Here is like to be a good presence of Worthies. He</l>
                  <l>presents Hector of Troy; the swain, Pompey the</l>
                  <l>Great; the parish curate, Alexander; Armado's page,</l>
                  <l>Hercules; the pedant, Judas Maccabaeus: And if</l>

                  <l>these four Worthies in their first show thrive,</l>
                  <l>These four will change habits, and present the other
                     five.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>There is five in the first show.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>You are deceived; 'tis not so.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>The pedant, the braggart, the hedge-priest, the fool</l>
                  <l>and the boy:--</l>
                  <l>Abate throw at novum, and the whole world again</l>
                  <l>Cannot pick out five such, take each one in his vein.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>

                  <l>The ship is under sail, and here she comes amain.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Costard, for Pompey</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I Pompey am,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>You lie, you are not he.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I Pompey am,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>With libbard's head on knee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Well said, old mocker: I must needs be friends</l>
                  <l>with thee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>I Pompey am, Pompey surnamed the Big--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>The Great.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>It is, 'Great,' sir:--</l>
                  <l>Pompey surnamed the Great;</l>
                  <l>That oft in field, with targe and shield, did make</l>
                  <l>my foe to sweat:</l>

                  <l>And travelling along this coast, I here am come by
                     chance,</l>
                  <l>And lay my arms before the legs of this sweet lass of
                     France,</l>
                  <l>If your ladyship would say, 'Thanks, Pompey,' I had
                     done.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Great thanks, great Pompey.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>'Tis not so much worth; but I hope I was perfect: I</l>
                  <l>made a little fault in 'Great.'</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>My hat to a halfpenny, Pompey proves the best Worthy.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Sir Nathaniel, for Alexander</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>When in the world I lived, I was the world's</l>
                  <l>commander;</l>
                  <l>By east, west, north, and south, I spread my</l>
                  <l>conquering might:</l>
                  <l>My scutcheon plain declares that I am Alisander,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>

                  <l>Your nose says, no, you are not for it stands too
                     right.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Your nose smells 'no' in this, most tender-smelling
                     knight.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>The conqueror is dismay'd. Proceed, good Alexander.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Nathaniel</speaker>
                  <l>When in the world I lived, I was the world's</l>
                  <l>commander,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Most true, 'tis right; you were so, Alisander.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Pompey the Great,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Your servant, and Costard.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>Take away the conqueror, take away Alisander.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l><stage>To Sir Nathaniel</stage> O, sir, you have
                     overthrown</l>
                  <l>Alisander the conqueror! You will be scraped out of</l>
                  <l>the painted cloth for this: your lion, that holds</l>
                  <l>his poll-axe sitting on a close-stool, will be given</l>

                  <l>to Ajax: he will be the ninth Worthy. A conqueror,</l>
                  <l>and afeard to speak! run away for shame, Alisander.</l>
                  <stage>Sir Nathaniel retires</stage>
                  <l>There, an't shall please you; a foolish mild man; an</l>
                  <l>honest man, look you, and soon dashed. He is a</l>
                  <l>marvellous good neighbour, faith, and a very good</l>
                  <l>bowler: but, for Alisander,--alas, you see how</l>
                  <l>'tis,--a little o'erparted. But there are Worthies</l>
                  <l>a-coming will speak their mind in some other sort.</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Holofernes, for Judas; and Moth, for
                  Hercules</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Great Hercules is presented by this imp,</l>
                  <l>Whose club kill'd Cerberus, that three-headed canis;</l>
                  <l>And when he was a babe, a child, a shrimp,</l>
                  <l>Thus did he strangle serpents in his manus.</l>

                  <l>Quoniam he seemeth in minority,</l>
                  <l>Ergo I come with this apology.</l>
                  <l>Keep some state in thy exit, and vanish.</l>
                  <stage>Moth retires</stage>
                  <l>Judas I am,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>A Judas!</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Not Iscariot, sir.</l>
                  <l>Judas I am, ycliped Maccabaeus.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Judas Maccabaeus clipt is plain Judas.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>A kissing traitor. How art thou proved Judas?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Judas I am,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>

                  <l>The more shame for you, Judas.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>What mean you, sir?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>To make Judas hang himself.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>Begin, sir; you are my elder.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Well followed: Judas was hanged on an elder.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>

                  <l>I will not be put out of countenance.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Because thou hast no face.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>What is this?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>A cittern-head.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>The head of a bodkin.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>A Death's face in a ring.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>The face of an old Roman coin, scarce seen.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>The pommel of Caesar's falchion.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>The carved-bone face on a flask.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Saint George's half-cheek in a brooch.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>

                  <l>Ay, and in a brooch of lead.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, and worn in the cap of a tooth-drawer.</l>
                  <l>And now forward; for we have put thee in countenance.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>You have put me out of countenance.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>False; we have given thee faces.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>But you have out-faced them all.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>An thou wert a lion, we would do so.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore, as he is an ass, let him go.</l>
                  <l>And so adieu, sweet Jude! nay, why dost thou stay?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>

                  <l>For the latter end of his name.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>For the ass to the Jude; give it him:--Jud-as, away!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Holofernes</speaker>
                  <l>This is not generous, not gentle, not humble.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>A light for Monsieur Judas! it grows dark, he may
                     stumble.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Holofernes retires</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, poor Maccabaeus, how hath he been baited!</l>

               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Don Adriano, for Hector</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Hide thy head, Achilles: here comes Hector in arms.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Though my mocks come home by me, I will now be merry.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Hector was but a Troyan in respect of this.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>But is this Hector?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>I think Hector was not so clean-timbered.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>His leg is too big for Hector's.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>More calf, certain.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>No; he is best endued in the small.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>This cannot be Hector.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>He's a god or a painter; for he makes faces.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>The armipotent Mars, of lances the almighty,</l>
                  <l>Gave Hector a gift,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>

                  <l>A gilt nutmeg.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>A lemon.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>Stuck with cloves.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>No, cloven.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Peace!--</l>
                  <l>The armipotent Mars, of lances the almighty</l>
                  <l>Gave Hector a gift, the heir of Ilion;</l>

                  <l>A man so breathed, that certain he would fight; yea</l>
                  <l>From morn till night, out of his pavilion.</l>
                  <l>I am that flower,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>That mint.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>

                  <l>That columbine.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Lord Longaville, rein thy tongue.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>I must rather give it the rein, for it runs against
                     Hector.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, and Hector's a greyhound.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>The sweet war-man is dead and rotten; sweet chucks,</l>
                  <l>beat not the bones of the buried: when he breathed,</l>
                  <l>he was a man. But I will forward with my device.</l>

                  <stage>To the Princess</stage>
                  <l>Sweet royalty, bestow on me the sense of hearing.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Speak, brave Hector: we are much delighted.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I do adore thy sweet grace's slipper.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside to Dumain</stage> Loves her by the foot,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l><stage>Aside to Boyet</stage> He may not by the yard.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>This Hector far surmounted Hannibal,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>The party is gone, fellow Hector, she is gone; she</l>
                  <l>is two months on her way.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>What meanest thou?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Faith, unless you play the honest Troyan, the poor</l>
                  <l>wench is cast away: she's quick; the child brags in</l>
                  <l>her belly already: tis yours.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Dost thou infamonize me among potentates? thou shalt</l>
                  <l>die.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>
                  <l>Then shall Hector be whipped for Jaquenetta that is</l>
                  <l>quick by him and hanged for Pompey that is dead by</l>

                  <l>him.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Most rare Pompey!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>Renowned Pompey!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Greater than great, great, great, great Pompey!</l>
                  <l>Pompey the Huge!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Hector trembles.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Pompey is moved. More Ates, more Ates! stir them</l>
                  <l>on! stir them on!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Hector will challenge him.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, if a' have no man's blood in's belly than will</l>
                  <l>sup a flea.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>By the north pole, I do challenge thee.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>I will not fight with a pole, like a northern man:</l>
                  <l>I'll slash; I'll do it by the sword. I bepray you,</l>
                  <l>let me borrow my arms again.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Room for the incensed Worthies!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Costard</speaker>

                  <l>I'll do it in my shirt.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Most resolute Pompey!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Moth</speaker>
                  <l>Master, let me take you a buttonhole lower. Do you</l>
                  <l>not see Pompey is uncasing for the combat? What mean</l>

                  <l>you? You will lose your reputation.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen and soldiers, pardon me; I will not combat</l>
                  <l>in my shirt.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>You may not deny it: Pompey hath made the challenge.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet bloods, I both may and will.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>What reason have you for't?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>The naked truth of it is, I have no shirt; I go</l>
                  <l>woolward for penance.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boyet</speaker>
                  <l>True, and it was enjoined him in Rome for want of</l>
                  <l>linen: since when, I'll be sworn, he wore none but</l>
                  <l>a dishclout of Jaquenetta's, and that a' wears next</l>

                  <l>his heart for a favour.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Enter Mercade</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mercade</speaker>
                  <l>God save you, madam!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Welcome, Mercade;</l>
                  <l>But that thou interrupt'st our merriment.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mercade</speaker>
                  <l>I am sorry, madam; for the news I bring</l>
                  <l>Is heavy in my tongue. The king your father--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Dead, for my life!</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mercade</speaker>
                  <l>Even so; my tale is told.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Worthies, away! the scene begins to cloud.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>For mine own part, I breathe free breath. I have</l>
                  <l>seen the day of wrong through the little hole of</l>
                  <l>discretion, and I will right myself like a soldier.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Exeunt Worthies</stage>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>How fares your majesty?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Boyet, prepare; I will away tonight.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, not so; I do beseech you, stay.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>Prepare, I say. I thank you, gracious lords,</l>
                  <l>For all your fair endeavors; and entreat,</l>
                  <l>Out of a new-sad soul, that you vouchsafe</l>
                  <l>In your rich wisdom to excuse or hide</l>
                  <l>The liberal opposition of our spirits,</l>
                  <l>If over-boldly we have borne ourselves</l>

                  <l>In the converse of breath: your gentleness</l>
                  <l>Was guilty of it. Farewell worthy lord!</l>
                  <l>A heavy heart bears not a nimble tongue:</l>
                  <l>Excuse me so, coming too short of thanks</l>
                  <l>For my great suit so easily obtain'd.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>The extreme parts of time extremely forms</l>

                  <l>All causes to the purpose of his speed,</l>
                  <l>And often at his very loose decides</l>
                  <l>That which long process could not arbitrate:</l>
                  <l>And though the mourning brow of progeny</l>
                  <l>Forbid the smiling courtesy of love</l>
                  <l>The holy suit which fain it would convince,</l>
                  <l>Yet, since love's argument was first on foot,</l>
                  <l>Let not the cloud of sorrow justle it</l>
                  <l>From what it purposed; since, to wail friends lost</l>

                  <l>Is not by much so wholesome-profitable</l>
                  <l>As to rejoice at friends but newly found.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>I understand you not: my griefs are double.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Honest plain words best pierce the ear of grief;</l>

                  <l>And by these badges understand the king.</l>
                  <l>For your fair sakes have we neglected time,</l>
                  <l>Play'd foul play with our oaths: your beauty, ladies,</l>
                  <l>Hath much deform'd us, fashioning our humours</l>
                  <l>Even to the opposed end of our intents:</l>
                  <l>And what in us hath seem'd ridiculous,--</l>
                  <l>As love is full of unbefitting strains,</l>
                  <l>All wanton as a child, skipping and vain,</l>
                  <l>Form'd by the eye and therefore, like the eye,</l>

                  <l>Full of strange shapes, of habits and of forms,</l>
                  <l>Varying in subjects as the eye doth roll</l>
                  <l>To every varied object in his glance:</l>
                  <l>Which parti-coated presence of loose love</l>
                  <l>Put on by us, if, in your heavenly eyes,</l>
                  <l>Have misbecomed our oaths and gravities,</l>
                  <l>Those heavenly eyes, that look into these faults,</l>
                  <l>Suggested us to make. Therefore, ladies,</l>
                  <l>Our love being yours, the error that love makes</l>

                  <l>Is likewise yours: we to ourselves prove false,</l>
                  <l>By being once false for ever to be true</l>
                  <l>To those that make us both,--fair ladies, you:</l>
                  <l>And even that falsehood, in itself a sin,</l>
                  <l>Thus purifies itself and turns to grace.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>We have received your letters full of love;</l>

                  <l>Your favours, the ambassadors of love;</l>
                  <l>And, in our maiden council, rated them</l>
                  <l>At courtship, pleasant jest and courtesy,</l>
                  <l>As bombast and as lining to the time:</l>
                  <l>But more devout than this in our respects</l>
                  <l>Have we not been; and therefore met your loves</l>
                  <l>In their own fashion, like a merriment.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>

                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>Our letters, madam, show'd much more than jest.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>So did our looks.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>We did not quote them so.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Now, at the latest minute of the hour,</l>
                  <l>Grant us your loves.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>
                  <l>A time, methinks, too short</l>
                  <l>To make a world-without-end bargain in.</l>

                  <l>No, no, my lord, your grace is perjured much,</l>
                  <l>Full of dear guiltiness; and therefore this:</l>
                  <l>If for my love, as there is no such cause,</l>
                  <l>You will do aught, this shall you do for me:</l>
                  <l>Your oath I will not trust; but go with speed</l>
                  <l>To some forlorn and naked hermitage,</l>
                  <l>Remote from all the pleasures of the world;</l>
                  <l>There stay until the twelve celestial signs</l>
                  <l>Have brought about the annual reckoning.</l>

                  <l>If this austere insociable life</l>
                  <l>Change not your offer made in heat of blood;</l>
                  <l>If frosts and fasts, hard lodging and thin weeds</l>
                  <l>Nip not the gaudy blossoms of your love,</l>
                  <l>But that it bear this trial and last love;</l>
                  <l>Then, at the expiration of the year,</l>
                  <l>Come challenge me, challenge me by these deserts,</l>
                  <l>And, by this virgin palm now kissing thine</l>
                  <l>I will be thine; and till that instant shut</l>

                  <l>My woeful self up in a mourning house,</l>
                  <l>Raining the tears of lamentation</l>
                  <l>For the remembrance of my father's death.</l>
                  <l>If this thou do deny, let our hands part,</l>
                  <l>Neither entitled in the other's heart.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>If this, or more than this, I would deny,</l>

                  <l>To flatter up these powers of mine with rest,</l>
                  <l>The sudden hand of death close up mine eye!</l>
                  <l>Hence ever then my heart is in thy breast.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>[And what to me, my love? and what to me?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>

                  <l>You must be purged too, your sins are rack'd,</l>
                  <l>You are attaint with faults and perjury:</l>
                  <l>Therefore if you my favour mean to get,</l>
                  <l>A twelvemonth shall you spend, and never rest,</l>
                  <l>But seek the weary beds of people sick.]</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>But what to me, my love? but what to me? A wife?</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>A beard, fair health, and honesty;</l>
                  <l>With three-fold love I wish you all these three.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>O, shall I say, I thank you, gentle wife?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Not so, my lord; a twelvemonth and a day</l>
                  <l>I'll mark no words that smooth-faced wooers say:</l>
                  <l>Come when the king doth to my lady come;</l>
                  <l>Then, if I have much love, I'll give you some.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>

                  <l>I'll serve thee true and faithfully till then.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Katherine</speaker>
                  <l>Yet swear not, lest ye be forsworn again.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>What says Maria?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>At the twelvemonth's end</l>
                  <l>I'll change my black gown for a faithful friend.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Longaville</speaker>
                  <l>I'll stay with patience; but the time is long.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria</speaker>
                  <l>The liker you; few taller are so young.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Studies my lady? mistress, look on me;</l>
                  <l>Behold the window of my heart, mine eye,</l>
                  <l>What humble suit attends thy answer there:</l>
                  <l>Impose some service on me for thy love.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Oft have I heard of you, my Lord Biron,</l>
                  <l>Before I saw you; and the world's large tongue</l>
                  <l>Proclaims you for a man replete with mocks,</l>
                  <l>Full of comparisons and wounding flouts,</l>
                  <l>Which you on all estates will execute</l>
                  <l>That lie within the mercy of your wit.</l>

                  <l>To weed this wormwood from your fruitful brain,</l>
                  <l>And therewithal to win me, if you please,</l>
                  <l>Without the which I am not to be won,</l>
                  <l>You shall this twelvemonth term from day to day</l>
                  <l>Visit the speechless sick and still converse</l>
                  <l>With groaning wretches; and your task shall be,</l>
                  <l>With all the fierce endeavor of your wit</l>
                  <l>To enforce the pained impotent to smile.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>To move wild laughter in the throat of death?</l>
                  <l>It cannot be; it is impossible:</l>
                  <l>Mirth cannot move a soul in agony.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rosaline</speaker>
                  <l>Why, that's the way to choke a gibing spirit,</l>

                  <l>Whose influence is begot of that loose grace</l>
                  <l>Which shallow laughing hearers give to fools:</l>
                  <l>A jest's prosperity lies in the ear</l>
                  <l>Of him that hears it, never in the tongue</l>
                  <l>Of him that makes it: then, if sickly ears,</l>
                  <l>Deaf'd with the clamours of their own dear groans,</l>
                  <l>Will hear your idle scorns, continue then,</l>
                  <l>And I will have you and that fault withal;</l>
                  <l>But if they will not, throw away that spirit,</l>

                  <l>And I shall find you empty of that fault,</l>
                  <l>Right joyful of your reformation.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>A twelvemonth! well; befall what will befall,</l>
                  <l>I'll jest a twelvemonth in an hospital.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l><stage>To Ferdinand</stage> Ay, sweet my lord; and so I
                     take my leave.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>No, madam; we will bring you on your way.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>
                  <l>Our wooing doth not end like an old play;</l>

                  <l>Jack hath not Jill: these ladies' courtesy</l>
                  <l>Might well have made our sport a comedy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Come, sir, it wants a twelvemonth and a day,</l>
                  <l>And then 'twill end.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Biron</speaker>

                  <l>That's too long for a play.</l>
               </sp>


               <stage>Re-enter Don Adriano</stage>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet majesty, vouchsafe me,--</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Princess</speaker>

                  <l>Was not that Hector?</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dumain</speaker>
                  <l>The worthy knight of Troy.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>I will kiss thy royal finger, and take leave. I am</l>
                  <l>a votary; I have vowed to Jaquenetta to hold the</l>

                  <l>plough for her sweet love three years. But, most</l>
                  <l>esteemed greatness, will you hear the dialogue that</l>
                  <l>the two learned men have compiled in praise of the</l>
                  <l>owl and the cuckoo? It should have followed in the</l>
                  <l>end of our show.</l>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferdinand</speaker>
                  <l>Call them forth quickly; we will do so.</l>

               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>Holla! approach.</l>
                  <stage>Re-enter Holofernes, Sir Nathaniel, Moth, Costard, and
                     others</stage>
                  <l>This side is Hiems, Winter, this Ver, the Spring;</l>
                  <l>the one maintained by the owl, the other by the</l>
                  <l>cuckoo. Ver, begin.</l>
                  <stage>The song</stage>

                  <lg type="song">
                     <head>Spring</head>
                     <l>When daisies pied and violets blue</l>
                     <l>And lady-smocks all silver-white</l>
                     <l>And cuckoo-buds of yellow hue</l>
                     <l>Do paint the meadows with delight,</l>
                     <l>The cuckoo then, on every tree,</l>
                     <l>Mocks married men; for thus sings he, Cuckoo;</l>
                     <l>Cuckoo, cuckoo: O word of fear,</l>
                     <l>Unpleasing to a married ear!</l>
                     <l>When shepherds pipe on oaten straws</l>
                     <l>And merry larks are ploughmen's clocks,</l>
                     <l>When turtles tread, and rooks, and daws,</l>
                     <l>And maidens bleach their summer smocks</l>
                     <l>The cuckoo then, on every tree,</l>
                     <l>Mocks married men; for thus sings he, Cuckoo;</l>
                     <l>Cuckoo, cuckoo: O word of fear,</l>
                     <l>Unpleasing to a married ear!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <head>Winter</head>
                     <l>When icicles hang by the wall</l>
                     <l>And Dick the shepherd blows his nail</l>
                     <l>And Tom bears logs into the hall</l>
                     <l>And milk comes frozen home in pail,</l>
                     <l>When blood is nipp'd and ways be foul,</l>
                     <l>Then nightly sings the staring owl, Tu-whit;</l>
                     <l>Tu-who, a merry note,</l>
                     <l>While greasy Joan doth keel the pot.</l>
                     <l>When all aloud the wind doth blow</l>
                     <l>And coughing drowns the parson's saw</l>
                     <l>And birds sit brooding in the snow</l>
                     <l>And Marian's nose looks red and raw,</l>
                     <l>When roasted crabs hiss in the bowl,</l>
                     <l>Then nightly sings the staring owl, Tu-whit;</l>
                     <l>Tu-who, a merry note,</l>
                     <l>While greasy Joan doth keel the pot.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don Adriano</speaker>
                  <l>The words of Mercury are harsh after the songs of</l>
                  <l>Apollo. You that way: we this way.</l>
               </sp>

               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
